<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The ungirding of the Scottish armour: or, An ansvver to the informations for defensive armes against the Kings Majestie which were drawn up at Edenburgh, by the common help and industrie of the three tables of the rigid covenanters of the nobility, barons, ministry, and burgesses, and ordained to be read out of pulpit by each minister, and pressed upon the people, to draw them to take up armes, to resist the Lords anointed, throughout the vvhole kingdome of Scotland. By Iohn Corbet, minister of Bonyl, one of the collegiate churches of the provostrie of Dunbartan.</title>
            <author>Nicanor, Lysimachus, 1603-1641.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1639</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 142 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 34 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A19328</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 5753</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119005</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854212</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854212</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19621</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A19328)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19621)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1133:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The ungirding of the Scottish armour: or, An ansvver to the informations for defensive armes against the Kings Majestie which were drawn up at Edenburgh, by the common help and industrie of the three tables of the rigid covenanters of the nobility, barons, ministry, and burgesses, and ordained to be read out of pulpit by each minister, and pressed upon the people, to draw them to take up armes, to resist the Lords anointed, throughout the vvhole kingdome of Scotland. By Iohn Corbet, minister of Bonyl, one of the collegiate churches of the provostrie of Dunbartan.</title>
                  <author>Nicanor, Lysimachus, 1603-1641.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 56 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by the Society of Stationers [i.e. R. Hodgkinson],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Dublin [i.e. London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1639.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Lysimachus Nicanor = John Corbet.</note>
                  <note>Imprint false; actual place of publication and printer from STC.</note>
                  <note>Title page has 24 fleur-de-lis and 2 rules; B1r line 3 of text ends: "cove-"; E4r line 5 begins: "common wealth. Answ. [in italics]".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Covenanters --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19621:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19621:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE VNGIRDING OF THE Scottish Armour: <hi>OR,</hi> AN ANSVVER TO THE Informations for Defenſive Armes againſt the Kings Majeſtie, which were drawn up at <hi>Edenburgh,</hi> by the common help and induſtrie of the three Tables of the rigid Covenanters of the Nobility, Barons, Miniſtry, and Burgeſſes, and ordained to be read out of Pulpit by each Miniſter, and preſſed upon the people, to draw them to take up armes, to reſiſt the <hi>Lords Anointed,</hi> throughout the whole Kingdome of SCOTLAND.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Iohn Corbet,</hi> Miniſter of <hi>Bonyl,</hi> one of the Collegiate Churches of the Provoſtrie of <hi>Dunbartan.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. 24.21.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>My Son feare God and the King, and meddle not with thoſe that are given to change. For their calamity ſhall riſe ſuddenly, and who knoweth the ruine of them both?</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Mat. 26.52.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Put up thy ſword into his place, for he that takes the ſword, ſhall periſh with the ſword.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>D<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>BLIN,</hi> Printed by the Society of Stationers, 1639.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:19621:2"/>
            <p>Perlegi hunc librum, cui Titulus eſt, <hi>[The ungir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the Scottiſh Armour]</hi> in quo nihil re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perio quo minus cum utilitate publica imprimatur.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>ED. PARRY,</hi> Reverendiſsimi in Chriſto Patris Archiepiſcopi Dublin. Sacellanus.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Maii ſexto, 1639.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:19621:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOURABLE, <hi>THOMAS,</hi> Lord Viſcount VVENTVVORTH, Baron of Wentworth Woodhouſe, Lord Newmarſh and Overſley, Lord Preſident of the Councell eſtabliſhed in the North part of <hi>England,</hi> Lord Lieutenant of <hi>York-ſhire,</hi> One of His Majeſties moſt Honourable Privie Councell in <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>Lord Deputie Generall of Jreland.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ince the Flood of our Scottiſh Diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and Vproares have overflowed the banks of divine and humane Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, I have beene with <hi>Jeremie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 9.1.</note> crying out in the bitterneſſe of my ſoule, <hi>O that my head were wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and my eyes a fountaine of teares, that I might weepe day and night,</hi> for the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries of my Countrey people: Whereof a fiery-zealous Faction, have from day to day waxed ſo inſolent; that of equity they may challenge as their owne, that deſcription
<pb facs="tcp:19621:3"/>which <hi>Jeremie</hi> affords in the next words,<note place="margin">Ier. 9.2.</note> 
               <hi>verſ. 2. They proceed from evill to evill, and are an aſſembly of treacherous men.</hi> For His Majeſties Clemencie hath been to them,<note place="margin">Prov. 16.15. Prov. 19 12.</note> 
               <hi>as a cloud of the latter raine;</hi> and <hi>as the dew on the graſſe;</hi> which ſhould have produced many re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnes of thankfulneſſe. But behold, he hath watered evill ground which bringeth forth briars and thornes the more abundantly.<note place="margin">Mich. 7.4 3.</note> 
               <hi>The beſt of them is as a briar; the moſt upright is as a thorn hedge: they do evill with both hands earneſtly; hunting every man his brother with a net. They are gone in the way of</hi> Cain, <hi>and run gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily after the errour of</hi> Balaam, <hi>and ſtand in the gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaying of</hi> Core Amongſt many paſſages to prove this, theſe their <hi>informations of warre</hi> are a moſt evident de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration, which cauſed me continue <hi>Jeremies</hi> Elegie and ſorrowfull Song: <hi>Oh that I had in the wilderneſſe a lodging of a way-faring man, that I might leave my people, and go from them.</hi> In the meane time, having purchaſed a copie of theſe informations, which with their Covenant now at laſt, with force and violence was to be thruſt and preſſed upon me, I returned this my Anſwer, whereof I was to make uſe with my Brethren at our next meeting (which was the ſeventh day after I had ſeen the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie) that they might ſee that as hitherto I could find no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to Covenant w th them, ſo now much leſſe, when it ends in open <hi>Rebellion.</hi> But being advertiſed of the cruell plot, and ſnares laid for me, I was forced to flie from the viru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and violent fury of the Covenant, as from a Beare robbed of her whelps, and to ſeek friends to vertue among ſtrangers: leaving my wife great with child, melting in ſorrow; with foure young children, to take a proofe of their humanity. When I came to this kingdome of <hi>Ireland,</hi> I was
<pb facs="tcp:19621:3"/>ſo aſhamed that ſuch treacherous doctrine ſhould have been brought forth by my Countrey-men, to the great ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall of the Goſpell, and deepe wounding of our protestant Religion, and rejoycing of the adverſaries, that I was pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing to ſmother theſe their informations: But ere I was maturely thus reſolved, I found the matter already ſpread abroad, and with my eyes have ſeene other copies. This did cut my reſolution in the blade, ſo that I ſuffered theſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formations with my anſwer to them, to enjoy the light. And that for diverſe reaſons. <hi>1.</hi> Becauſe ſome men (not knowing the Myſtery of the Covenant, nor that old ſaying of <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, In nomine Domini incipit omne malum</hi>) have thought it impoſsible, that ſuch rebellious doctrine could be hatched by the <hi>Covenanters,</hi> and that it ſeemeth to be an invention of others, to make them the more odious. This I refute, by publiſhing the ſame. Secondly, that this do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, whereunto I, one of the least of the Tribe of <hi>Levi</hi> there, have anſwered, may not be imputed to that Church and Nation, but to ſome factious ſpirits there, who have <hi>this houre and power of darkneſſe:</hi> For ſince the moſt part of them were compelled to ſubſcribe their covenant, ſhall any man think that they will allow this doctrine of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion? I know the contrary, and dare preſume to affirme, that the beſt of that Kingdome for worth and number, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of the Miniſtry, ſhall aſſent to that truth which I here maintaine, though now they be carried away with this inundation; and the lay-ruling-Biſhops their Govenours keep them under. Yea, my charity is ſo enlarged, that I trust, that the chiefe Contrivers of theſe informations ſhall acknowledge their errour: for they have been tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported with paſsions, whilſt they were upon this worke, by their <hi>great ſwelling words,</hi> fully ſtuffed with calumnies;
<pb facs="tcp:19621:4"/>whereof I hope they will repent in their cold bloud, when they forbeare to be as the <hi>raging waves of the ſea, fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming out their own ſhame.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iude 13. Eſa. 32.2.</note> Then <hi>the heart of the raſh ſhall underſtand knowledge.</hi> So that I hope the number ſhall be few, as the grape-gleanings after the vintage, who defend this mad doctrine:<note place="margin">Acts 28.19.</note> And I, with <hi>Paul, ſhall have nothing to accuſe my Nation of.</hi> But if any, after ripe deliberation, ſhall adhere to this rebellious doctrine, and when they ſhould cry,
<q>Nulla ſalus bello, pacem te petimus omnes,</q>ſhall change it into
<q>Tota ſalus bello, facem te petimus omnes,</q>I ſhall be ſo farre from contradicting thoſe who have cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led them all mad men, that I ſhall take up <hi>Pauls</hi> wiſh, <hi>I would to God that they were both altogether,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 26.29.</note> 
               <hi>and almoſt even as</hi> Paul, <hi>his bonds not</hi> being excepted; which bonds I wiſh not as a puniſhment, but as a remedy for their brain-ſick malady: having withall their <hi>Camp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticks</hi> taken from them,<note place="margin">Pro. 26.18.</note> as being moſt dangerous in the hands of mad men, eſpecially for themſelves. And as for theſe Cynick and Lucinian railers, rather than preachers; ſuch as that wiſeman who made ſport in the Pulpit of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denburgh,</hi> by riding <hi>Balaams aſſe:</hi> and that other mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cap who wounded the beast, theſe are wiſe enough for their new calling, let them be gone to them. Let the one learn bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to play the <hi>butcher</hi> with beaſts, whoſe Phyſicke for man is naught: and let the other be an <hi>Aſſe-breaker,</hi> and if he did formerly thus preach, I am ſure an Aſſe hath done more ſervice to Christ than ever he hath done: an <hi>Aſſe</hi> caried Chriſt to leruſalem, but with his <hi>Aſinine pratlings</hi> he hath brought none to Chriſt. And therefore I would not that any ſhould brand our Church with ſuch <hi>ſpots, fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe
<pb facs="tcp:19621:4"/>trees, wandring ſtars,</hi> and <hi>clouds without water:</hi> Let them beare their own ſhame. It cannot be dennyed, but our Church is now in a great Eclipſe, and the mouth of our common adverſary is open, and they triumphing over us, cry, <hi>Medice te ipſum cura:</hi> But,<note place="margin">Mic. 7.8.</note> 
               <hi>Rejoyce not againſt me, O mine enemy, though I have fallen, I ſhall ariſe; though I ſit in darkneſſe, the Lord ſhall be a light un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me.</hi> I hope to ſee our Church <hi>flouriſhing</hi> and <hi>ſhining</hi> in her former <hi>beauty,</hi> maintaining againe the Orthodoxe Doctrine toward <hi>Monarchy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.15.</note> and <hi>putting to ſilence the ignorance of fooliſh men.</hi> And therefore, my third reaſon in publiſhing this Treatiſe is, that all our Orthodoxe Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines may have theſe informations, as ſo many <hi>Theſes,</hi> brought to their hands, who are more able to ſtop the mouth of the Gain-ſayers.</p>
            <p>Now, <hi>Right Honourable</hi> ſeeing I am a ſtranger in this Kingdome, and this my meane labour ſtandeth in need of one (in theſe evill dayes) who is powerfull both for Place, and Learning, for its <hi>Patron:</hi> I have therefore preſumed to lay it at your Lordſhips feet, begging your honourable <hi>Patronage,</hi> in whom both great <hi>Authority</hi> and <hi>Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Wiſdome</hi> and <hi>Juſtice</hi> are met; whom this Church and Nation hath found a moſt gratious <hi>Patron.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 24.10.</note> 
               <hi>Whom I know to have been of many yeeres a governour unto this nation;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 26.3.</note> 
               <hi>and to be expert in all cuſtomes and queſtions</hi> of this nature, which concerneth the civill Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, and eſpecially the Monarchicall Government of great <hi>King CHARLES.</hi> And therefore, though the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor and the workmanſhip be but mean and rude, yet the matter which I defend, deſervedly craveth ſuch a high Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage for its defence, as is your Lordſhip; who is as faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>David, among all the Kings ſervants, and honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
<pb facs="tcp:19621:5"/>in his houſe;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 22 14. Iob. 29.14.</note> who hath <hi>put on Righteouſneſſe as a cloathing, and judgment as a robe and diademe;</hi> whom, <hi>when thy eare heareth, it bleſſeth; and when thy eye ſeeth, it giveth witneſſe, as to one ready to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver the poore that cryeth, and the fatherleſſe, and him that hath none to help, and to break the jawes of the unrighteous, and to plucke the ſpoile out of his teeth.</hi> And this is no ſmall addition to his Majeſties hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe,<note place="margin">Pſal. 101.6.</note> to have <hi>one who walketh in a perfect way to ſerve him,</hi> which was <hi>Davids</hi> reſolution. As <hi>Salomon</hi> ſpeaketh of the vertuous woman,<note place="margin">Prov. 31 11.</note> 
               <hi>The heart of her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band doth ſafely truſt in her, ſo that he ſhall have no need of ſpoile:</hi> So may I ſay of his Majeſties truſt in your Lordſhip, eſpecially in theſe evill dayes, which brings to my remembrance the words of <hi>Nabal.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 25.10.</note> 
               <hi>There be many ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants now adayes, that breake away every man from his Maſter.</hi> To put confidence in ſuch, is to trust to a bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken tooth, and to a foot out of joynt.</p>
            <p>May it pleaſe therefore your Lordſhip favourably to accept theſe meane labours, which for the Glory of God, Victory of truth, honour of our King, and good will to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward my diſtracted Countrey-men, I have brought to light; Humbly beſeeching for the ſhelter of your L. protection, to this Treatiſe and its Author, who ſhall begin and remaine to bee</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips moſt humble Servant, JOHN CORBET.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:19621:5"/>
            <head>THE VNGIRDING OF THE Scotish Armour.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Elephant travelleth not ſo long from her conception to her birth, as theſe chiefe cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanters have been travelling in their mutuall bond of defence againſt authority, under the Cloak of a Covenant with <hi>God,</hi> to bring forth this huge, and monſtrous birth of informati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for reſiſting the Lords A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noynted; who after unparallel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led examples of Clemencie, is conſtrained by force of Armes to re-eſtabliſh his Ancient Authoritie in SCOTLAND, which is now laid in the duſt, and trampled under foot. At this laſt meeting at <hi>Edenburgh,</hi> of the Nobilitie, Barons, and learnedſt of the rigid covenanting Mininſterie, for this effect, I looked for ſome great matter, for ſome weighty, and powerfull arguments and reaſons to preſſe the people to Armes, but behold, <hi>they have brought forth nought but a lie,</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:19621:6"/>as ſayes the Royall Prophet <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 7.14. not ſo much as a ſhadow of any ſound reaſon, to any reaſonable man,
<q>Parturiunt montes, naſcetur ridiculus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>us.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And I proteſt that I am now beyond all Admiration, when I conſider how ſo many men can be carried away with ſo ſmall appearance of reaſon from the due ſubjection to the ſupreme Governour under God, and not bee moved when moſt ſound reaſons are brought on the contrary, but rather furiouſly, with the zeale of <hi>Iehu,</hi> perſecute thoſe who upon ſound reaſons withſtand them in great ſobriety. This is a great prejudice, and its moſt manifeſt that their affections obnubilates their reaſons, as ſinoake, that they cannot ſee. For our miniſters of the ſtrict and rigid ſort have taken only paines in moving the affections, and not in inſtructing the mind with ſound reaſons; hereunto like the falſe teachers, who (as witneſſeth <hi>Tertullian</hi>) <hi>priùs ſuadent quàm docent:</hi> Hence it is that in this Pamphlet of theirs, before they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge any reaſons of their reſiſting authority, they propound ſix points, for the gaining of the affections of the people, and then come to ſome naughtie reaſons to perſwade warre. I know that the times are evill, I have already ſuffered much thereof, ſo that <hi>Amos</hi> counſell, <hi>chap</hi> 5.13. might ſeeme ſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, <hi>The prudent ſhall keepe ſilence in that time, for it is an evill time,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſa. 59.15.</note> Yea, ſo evill a time, that hee <hi>who departs from evill, makes himſelfe a prey;</hi> as <hi>Iſaias</hi> ſayes.</p>
            <p>But when I ſee hoſtile armes raiſed againſt our dread So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigue, the Lords Anoynted, the breath of our Noſtrils; I cannot hold my peace any longer, but as the dumbe ſonne of King <hi>Croeſus</hi> ſuddainely ſpake when he ſaw the ſword upon the King his father, crying, <hi>O man kill not the King.</hi> So when I ſee the ſame to be drawne againſt my father, my King, and Head, I cannot hold my peace, and I cry rather, O Country men, ſave your ſelves from ſuch high rebellion. Save your ſoules, ſave your bodies and eſtates: be affraid to under-take that Warre which is forbidden by God, adventure not a poore ſoule upon ſuch an hazzard, in reſiſting ſuperior pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, which is to reſiſt the Ordinance of God, and will you
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:19621:6"/>ſtrive with the Almighty? I have conſidered your reaſons, drawne up at your tables for Armes, and I find no reaſon that any ſoule may probably lean to. Vpon the firſt ſight of them, my duty to God, my King, and Country, ſuffered me not to ſleepe till I had returned this ſhort anſwer, which I wiſh might come to your hands without ſuppreſſion, till time and leaſure be granted more fully to anſwer this point. As your armes (you ſay) are for defence, ſo is my Pen; let the learned turne their Pen againſt mine, if they finde no ſatisfaction, and let the ſword be againſt the armies of the Aliens: for my Pen here is not offenſive, but defenſive, let us firſt fight with our Pennes, and if yours be conquerours, then goe to ſwords. I ſhall keepe this Method, to ſet downe word by word all your inſtructions without miſſing a ſyllable, and then return an anſwer, not ſo much as it deſerveth, but as I thinke expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to anſwer.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Covenanters inſtructions.</head>
               <head type="sub">The times require that the points following be preſſed upon the people, both by the Preachers in publicke, and understanding and well-affected Profeſſors in private conferences.</head>
               <p n="1">1. BEcauſe our chiefe adverſaries, who are enemies to the Goſpell of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> to the ſalvation of the peoples ſoules and to the peace of this Church and Kingdome, have from the beginning advanced their ungodly and Antichriſtian courſe, by lies and perſecution, by craft and cruelty, which have beene their moſt ſubtill and ſtrongeſt arguments. And now when by excommunication they are given over to Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan who hath been a lier and murtherer from the beginning, have put away all conſcience, countenance, and naturall affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions to their Country, the people would bee dealt withall that their fraudulent lies and crafty devices be not beleeved, nor their force and threatned violence be feared by the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:19621:7"/>of God, remembring their Helliſh Maxime:
<q>Flectere ſi nequeo ſuperos, Acheront a movebo.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Anticovenanter.</head>
               <p>Though much might bee ſaid againſt this moſt unchriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an and uncharitable divelliſh ſaying, which I might juſtly retort, eſpecially in perſwading the people to ſweare to ſerve the King, which ſervice you now cauſe ſtand in reſiſting; Yet with <hi>Michael</hi> the Archangell, diſputing with the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill about the body of <hi>Moſes,</hi> I will bring no railing accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,<note place="margin">Iude 9.</note> but I ſay, <hi>The Lord rebuke thee.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Covenanter.</head>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2.</hi> That <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitie bee earneſtly recommended, as that which ſtrengthens the cauſe, and which being faſt holden with veritie, will make us invincible: and on the contrary, that Diviſion is by all meanes to bee avoyded, as that which from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning hath beene principally intended, and many wayes ſought for by our enemies, and which once having place, will bring us to a certaine ruine, and make us of all people the moſt contempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and miſerable; expoſing our ſelves and our poſteritie, to the wrath of God, for our perfidious dealing in his Covenant, to the mercileſſe crueltie of our enemies, to be a hiſſing and reproach to all Nations about us, and to be a griefe to all godly, who have beene continually in their prayers and praiſes to God for us all this time.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Anticovenanter.</head>
               <p n="1">1. You have great cauſe to urge unitie, for if even Satans kingdome be divided, it cannot ſtand. 2. Let unitie with the head be urged, and not of the members againſt the head; to recommend unitie, and not with the head, is in effect, to urge ſeparation and diviſion, to ſcatter in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and divide in <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob;</hi> which thing you here doe unhappily preſage, <hi>male
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:19621:7"/>ominatis parcite verbis.</hi> 3. No diviſion hath beene intended, but the right union hath beene ſought for, which is between the head and the reſt of the body, the King and his ſubjects, which you now have ſo much withſtood, ſeeking only uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the members without the head, which is to make one monſter of many heads, as is ſeene amongſt us this day.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Eſt bydr a multorum capitum; variabile vulgus,</l>
                  <l>Seditione potens.</l>
               </q>
               <p>And certainely, there is ſuch Antipathie in this your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſederation, that you cannot be well united; you are like un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Nebuchadnezars</hi> image, not all of one mettall, gold, ſilver, braſſe, yron and clay, of which ſimples, none can compound a perfect body: you of the young Nobility, who will be the golden head, you of the Gentrie, who will be the breſt of ſilver, you Burgeſſes, who will be the brazen thighes, you ſilly Miniſters, who are placed in the foot by the order of your Covenant, to be yron, mixt with the Commons, the clay; whoſe dwelling is of the clay, and habitation of the duſt, how can you have any durable union? If you march forward, your foot of clay muſt faile you, and you muſt fall and breake your golden heads, like <hi>Dagon</hi> before the Arke, and nothing be left, but a ſtump of antipathizing mettall,</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Covenanter.</head>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3.</hi> That it be frequently remembred, how the finger and power of God by many and admirable evidences hath beene manifeſt in this great worke of reformation, and how the Lord either by blowing upon all the deviſes of our enemies; or by turning them backe upon themſelves, hath turned all their wiſedome into fooliſhneſſe, that we may have confidence for time to come, belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, and ſaying with the Prophet, Jſa. <hi>26. Lord, thou wilt ordaine peace for us.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Anticovenanter.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <l>—<hi>Careat ſucceſſibus opto,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Quiſquis ab eventu facta notanda putet.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:19621:8"/>
It's ever eſteemed fooliſhneſſe to argue of the goodneſſe of any enterprize from the ſucceſſe thereof. <hi>Diagoras</hi> the Atheiſt was confirmed in his opinion that there was no God, becauſe he came with a faire gale of wind through the Sea without ſhipwracke.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Polycrates</hi> the Tyrant of Samos was renouned above all that ever I read in prophane Hiſtory, for his proſperity and good ſucceſſe in all his buſineſſe, and when by his friends he was deſired to ſeeke adverſity in ſome thing, becauſe they thought it ominous, never to taſte of troubles; he threw a moſt precious ring into the river, the loſſe whereof grieved him much, but the next morning his Cook found the ring in the belly of a fiſh, which confirmed the Tyrant in his opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of perpetuall proſperity, but yet in the end he was taken by <hi>Orontes,</hi> and hanged. Men ought not to bleſſe themſelves in any evill way, and ſay in their hearts we ſhall never bee moved. Reade the League of France, and you ſhall ſee how they proſper'd in al their affaires. The Lacqueies of the Duke of <hi>Guize</hi> had more credit with the people then his Majeſties principall Servants: ſo is it now with you, your cup is not yet full, behold the end. The Kings Clemency hath made you inſolent, if hee at the beginning had ſhowne himſelfe like a blazing Star, you had all evaniſhed as ſmoak, but his Majeſty being a follower of God his Maſter hath thought by clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie and indulgence to gaine you, and now ſeeth that Iuſtice muſt ſucceed to clemency, to bring you to ſubjection; neither ſhall you eſcape by iniquity, and the further ye proceed in an evill way, the neerer is your ruine.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Covenanter.</head>
               <p n="4">
                  <hi>4.</hi> That the people bee not troubled when they heare of wars, nor affraid of ſhadowes, nor be deceived with promiſes, nor mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved with remonstrances were they never ſo ſpecious, but they themſelves denounce Warre againſt their owne ſinnes, as their greateſt enemies, and ſubmit themſelves obediently to follow their Leaders, whom God at this time hath largely furniſhed
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:19621:8"/>with counſell, and courage, for the good of his Kirk, and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Anticovenanter.</head>
               <p>The people needeth not to bee troubled with warres,<note place="margin">Rom. 13.3.</note> if they be loyall Subjects, for his Majeſty is not <hi>a terror to good workes, but to the evill. Wilt thou then not be afraid of the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er? doe that which is good, and thou ſhalt have the praiſe of the ſame. For he is the Miniſter of God to thee for good: but if thou doe that which is evill, bee afraid: for hee beareth not the ſword in vaine: for he is the Miniſter of God, a revenger to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecute wrath upon him that doth evill.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. It's needleſſe to perſwade them not to be afraid of ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes, for ſhadowes flie away. But what meane you by ſhadowes? the Kings power? his armie? Well, it may be that theſe ſhadowes become bodies. <hi>Zebul</hi> perſwaded <hi>Gaal</hi> who conſpired againſt <hi>Abimelech,</hi> that <hi>Abimelech</hi>'s army was but the <hi>ſhadow of the mountaines,</hi> and not men.<note place="margin">Iudg. 9.36.</note> But when <hi>Gall</hi> ſaw them come downe by the middle <hi>of the land,</hi> and another company come along by the plaine in Meonenim: <hi>he found that a ſhadow to be feared,</hi> when <hi>Zebul</hi> ſaid, <hi>where is now thy mouth, wherewith thou ſaydst, Who is Abimelech, that we ſhould ſerve him? Is not this the people that thou haſt deſpiſed? Goe out, I pray now, and fight with him.</hi> Howbeit you regard not this ſhadow, yet let all theſe in his Dominions that feare God, eſteeme His Majeſties power under God to be, eſpecially in theſe evill times, <hi>a hiding place from the wind, a covert from the tempeſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſa. 32.2.</note> 
                  <hi>a ſhadow of a great rocke in a wearie Land.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Whereas you deſire men not to be <hi>deceived with promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, &amp;c.</hi> You would doe well to make this cleare. Will the King promiſe faire, and then faile? Will you like railing <hi>Rabſhakeh</hi> diſſwade Iſrael to truſt <hi>Hezekias?</hi> and ſay,<note place="margin">2 King. 18.29.</note> 
                  <hi>Let not the King deceive you, hearken not unto him:</hi> GOD give you better mindes. I dare bee bold to promiſe in His Majeſties name theſe words of the Prophet <hi>Eſay. Say to the righteous,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſa. 3.10.</note> 
                  <hi>that it ſhall bee well with him: for they ſhall eate the fruit of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:19621:9"/>their doings. Woe unto the wicked, it ſhall be evill with him, for the reward of his hands ſhall be given unto him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. It's well adviſed to urge the people to make <hi>war with ſinne,</hi> God further this worke; but I pary you, urge them to denounce warre againſt the reigning ſinne amongſt you, againſt <hi>rebellion, and reſiſting of ſuperiour Powers.</hi> Let the Leaders of Gods people lean them in the paths of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; bring not ſtrange fire to Gods Altar; warme not your pulpits with the ſtrange <hi>doctrine of unrighteouſneſſe;</hi> that you may at the day of account, ſay, <hi>Lord, I have done as thou haſt commanded,</hi> and <hi>if wee have beene deceived, thou haſt deceived us:</hi> and be not blind leaders of the blind, till you both fall in the ditch.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Covenanter.</head>
               <p n="5">
                  <hi>5.</hi> That is be remembred, what hath been our manifold defecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, in diſcipline, Sacraments, worſhip and doctrine, through the want of lawfull Nationall aſſemblies, and the uſurpation of the Prelats theſe many yeeres by past; and that a greater mercie could not be ſhowne to this Land, than a free and full Nae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall aſſemblie; ſuch as is that which was indicted by His Majeſtie, and holden at Glaſgow, ridding this Kirke of the Prelates, the Authors, and Executioners of all our woes. That they may bee earnest with God in their Prayers, that as he hath beene pleaſed to ſet up our reformation againe with a ſtretched out hand, hee may bee graciouſly pleaſed to uphold his own work; and make the Kings Majeſty a nurſing Father to the Kirke in this Land.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Anticovenanter.</head>
               <p>Let theſe things be remembred in Gods Name. Tell them, that the defections of Diſcipline is great, in that the antient Apoſtolik Government is by a lawles Covenant abjured, and by violence removed; and another of a baſer coin put in it's place. Tell them of the profanation of the Sacraments: and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:19621:9"/>of their ſuperſtitious opinion, who make ſome geſture eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall to the Lords Supper, and others idolatrous. Let them be told too, that the Lord is wronged in his worſhip, by thoſe who condemne ſet prayers in his Service. Tell them likewiſe, that the Doctrine is corrupted, eſpecially concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the authority of the Supreme Magiſtrate. But call not ye the Prelates, the authors and executioners of your woes, who are become ſo great enemies to them: you ought alſo to be afraid to father your diſorders upon God, as a work of reformation, thereby ſpeciouſly making him the author and fautor of all your miſdemeanours.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>After a contemptus ſpecies eſt, dicere falſum;</l>
                  <l>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> fidem facias, divine numine abuti.</l>
               </q>
               <p>And finally, it's a moſt odiouſly ſpoken by you, to pray that <hi>the King His Majeſtie may be a nurſing father to his Church;</hi> for in your ſenſe, you ſeeme to make him a ſtepfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, an enemy, yea, a Tyrant to the Church, as you declare your ſelves in the ſtating of the queſtion, and anſwering to the 13. <hi>Rom.</hi> for except he be a Tyrant, you declare it's un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull to reſiſt him: and if mercy, clemency, and all Royall vertues, which are in him, be Tyranny, then His Majeſtie is the greateſt Tyrant that ever was.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Covenanter.</head>
               <p n="6">
                  <hi>6</hi> That the Miniſters and Profeſſors acquaint themſelves with the acts of Aſſemblie, eſpecially that againſt Epiſcopacie, with the proteſtation and anſwers to the Declaration made by the <hi>Commiſſioner,</hi> and the Declinator of the Aſſemblie by the <hi>Biſhops:</hi> That from theſe, they may be able promptly to anſwer the objections of the Adverſaries. That the laſt ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication be read in publike, that the Commons may ſee how falſly we are traduced, and how reaſonable our deſire is.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Anticovenanter.</head>
               <p>It were more ſit that you ſhould ſtudie to prudencie, and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:19621:10"/>to keepe theſe things cloſe, and to deſire that theſe things ſhould not be told in <hi>Gath,</hi> not publiſhed in <hi>Askelon,</hi> eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, that monſtrous Act concerning <hi>Epiſcopacie;</hi> leſt by publiſhing theſe your follies in print, you make your ſelves, <hi>Opprobrium Coeli, ludibrium<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſoli.</hi> And get your Aſſembly branded with that of the Councell of <hi>Trent. Non fuit libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Concilium,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sibrand de Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil. Excep. <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>ſed combinatio conjuratorum.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Covenanter.</head>
               <p n="7">
                  <hi>7</hi> The ſtating of the Controverſie at this time betweene the King and his Subjects muſt be cleared to the people thus: that all men may know how unjuſtly we are invaded, and how juſt and neceſſary our defence ſhall be. The queſtion is not, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we ought honour to the King, for we a knowledge him to be Gods Deputie and Vicegerent: or whether we ought to obey the King, for God hath given him Power and Authority to Command: or whether we ought to given unto <hi>Caeſar,</hi> that which is <hi>Caeſars,</hi> for that we deſire to doe moſt cheerfully: or whether we ought to feare the King, for he is ſet over us to doe Juſtice. Neither is the question, whether Honour ſhould be given to evill Superiours, for as our Adverſaries, by moving of ſuch queſtions at this time under pretext of dutie, doe wrong and diſhonour to the Kings gracious Majeſtie; ſo we profeſſe in the generall, that the wickedneſſe of man cannot avoid Gods Ordinance: and therefore although we had froward and wicked Superiours, yet obedience and honour is to be given unto them, as being ſet up by God, as it were, in his wrath, <hi>Hoſ. 13.11.</hi> Neither is the queſtion, whether we ought abſolute obedience to an evill Magiſtrate, for our adverſaries (whatſoever be their judgement and practice) doe not affirme that <hi>malo in malo,</hi> or <hi>ad malum eſt obediendum,</hi> but that Kings are to be obeyed ſo farre as their Commandements are not contrary to Gods, and if God command one thing, and they the contrary; in this caſe, it's better to obey God, than man. Neither is the queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on about the invaſion of the King, or any of his Kingdomes, which is the deſpitefull and divelliſh calumnie of the diſnatured
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:19621:10"/>enemies of this Kirk and Kingdome. But the queſtion is meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſimply about our owne defence. And in this alſo wee would put difference betweene the King reſident in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and by opening his eares to both parties rightly inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and the King farre from us in another Kingdome, hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the parties, and miſinformed by our adverſaries: Between the King, as King proceeding Royally according to the lawes of the Kingdome against rebells, and the King comming downe from his Throne, at the feet whereof, the humble ſupplication of his ſubjects, yet lyeth ananſwered, furiouſly to invade his loyall and well-meaning people. Betweene a King, who is a ſtranger to religion, and tyed no further but according to his owne pleaſure to the profeſſors of Religion within his Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and our King profeſsing with us the ſame Religion, and obliged by his fathers deed and his owne oath, to defend us his owne Subjects, our lives, religion, liberties and lawes. Again, difference would be put betwixt ſome private perſons, taking armes for reſiſtance; and inferiour Magiſtrates, Counſellors, Iudges, Nobles and Peeres of the Land, Parliament-men and Barons, Burgeſſes, and the whole body of the Kingdome, except ſome few Courtiers, States-men, papiſts, or popiſhly affected. Betweene ſubjects riſing or ſtanding out against law and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that they may be free from the yoake of obedience, and a people holding faſt their alleageance to their Soveraigne, and in all humilitie ſupplicating for Religion and Iustice. Betweene a people labouring by Armes to introduce innovations in religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, contrary to Gods Word; and a people ſeeking nothing ſo much as againſt all novations, to have the ſame Religion ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified, which hath beene profeſſed ſince the reformation, and hath not onely beene ſworne to ſolemnly long ſince, by the Kings Majeſtie and the whole Kingdome, both of old and of late; but alſo commanded by the Kings Majeſtie to be ſworne by his Councellors, and all people, as it was profeſſed at firſt Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene a people pleading for their owne fancies, follies and inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and a people ſuſpending their judgement and practice about things controverted, till they ſhould be determined in a Nationall aſſemblie, the only proper and competent juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction;
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:19621:11"/>and after determination, receiving and ſtanding for the Acts of the Aſſemblie. The queſtion then is, whether in this caſe, matters thus ſtanding betwixt the King and this king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, defenſive warre be lawfull? or, whether the people ought to defend themſelves againſt extreame violence and oppreſſion, bringing utter ruine and deſolation upon the Kirk and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, upon themſelves and their poſteritie? That it is lawfull for us to take up Armes for our defence againſt ſuch unjuſt vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, it is manifeſt by theſe reaſons following.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Anticovenanter.</head>
               <p>I Many Tautologies are here uſed in ſtating the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie, and you remove that which is the queſtion, and makes that the queſtion, which I am perſwaded, you know to be not the queſtion. 2. You multiply words to affect the ignorant, the queſtion is not ſay you whether we ought to <hi>honour, obey</hi> or <hi>feare the King,</hi> or whether we ought to give <hi>Caeſar</hi> that which is <hi>Caeſars.</hi> Know you not that the laſt queſtion comprehends all theſe? is not <hi>honour, feare,</hi> and <hi>obedience, Caeſars due?</hi> 3. You are very <hi>charitable,</hi> that you ſay, whatever be out judgement and practice, yet we affirme in word, that abſolute obedience in evill is not to be given to wicked men. 4. You make many <hi>differences</hi> about <hi>defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive armes</hi> to no effect. The firſt difference, <hi>betweene the King reſident in the Kingdome, hearing impartially the complaint of both parties, &amp;c.</hi> I pray you tell me, if the King were here reſident, and did impartially heare you, and gave ſentence againſt you, would you not then reſiſt? Would you not even then be judges in your owne cauſe, and take up defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive armes? Whether the King be at home with you, or abroad, he ſhall ſtill be one <hi>partiall</hi> and unequall judge, ſo long as he goeth not with you. Your ſecond difference is of the like ſtuffe, <hi>Between the King proceeding by lawes, and the King comming furiouſly againſt his Subjects.</hi> His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie was ſtill well pleaſed, and ſo remaineth, to proceed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Laws: but you will not ſtand to his judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but muſt be judges in your owne cauſe: and now if
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:19621:11"/>his Majeſtie, after ſo long contempt of him, and his Lawes, bee forced to draw the ſword of Iuſtice, you cry out, hee commeth furiouſly againſt you. Your third difference is of the ſame nature, <hi>Betweene a King who is a ſtranger to religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and a King who is of the ſame with us.</hi> What make you the difference herein! Will you not reſiſt a ſtranger to reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, if he invade you by armes? The ſtranger to religion, by the Law of God, and his calling, is bound to defend the Religion within his Dominions, aſwell as our King; onely this, our King is more obliged by his generall calling of Chriſtianitie, and by his owne fact and deed: and bleſſed be God, he will ever do it. Your fourth difference is of no purpoſe alſo. <hi>Betweene a private man, and the whole bodie of a Kingdome for the moſt part, &amp;c.</hi> Tell me then, doe you grant, that one private man ought not to defend himſelfe againſt the Supreme Magiſtrate by armes? albeit, it bee true that he may not, and you doe here deny it; yet you muſt be forced to acknowledge the lawfulnes of it: for after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, your reaſon ſhall make it good, that you maintain the lawfulneſſe of a private mans taking up of armes, againſt the Lords anointed.</p>
               <p>You doe no ſmall in jurie to our Nation; to affirme that the whole bodie of the Kingdome, except a few, &amp;c. 1. For it's notorious, that the whole body of the Kingdome, for the moſt part, did never dreame of ſuch a thing, as to take up armes againſt the Lords anointed, but were moſt deceitfully parſwaded, that their covenant did not carry them to ſuch rebellion; but only to <hi>ſerve God,</hi> and <hi>their King.</hi> And now many of them are exclaiming, that they are deceived, and muſt be perjured, if they take armes againſt their King. And how many are groaning under this, and would gladly bee freed? and yet dare not for your terrours and affrightments. 2. They are many who have ſubſcribed the <hi>Kings Covenant,</hi> who will be loath to be in that Categorie with you: For I hope they know, that, beſide the ſinne of <hi>Rebellion,</hi> they will alſo incurre <hi>Perjurie,</hi> if they runne with you in your evill way. For they are obliged by their bond, to take up defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:19621:12"/>armes in defence of the <hi>King, Religion</hi> and <hi>Lawes;</hi> and that only when by <hi>Authoritie</hi> they are commanded ſo to do. But your <hi>covenant</hi> obliges you to take up armes againſt his Majeſtie, even though he forbid you; if by <hi>common conſent</hi> you think it ſhould be done.</p>
               <p>Your fifth difference is of the ſame nature too. <hi>Betweene a people holding faſt their alleagiance, &amp;c.</hi> If you be ſuch as you call your ſelves, his Majeſtie hath no quarrell againſt you, but herein yet you muſt be judges in your owne cauſe, and the King muſt ſtand to your ſentence. <hi>Saul</hi> was righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in his owne conceit, and did obey the Commandement of God, but the <hi>bleeting of the ſheepe,</hi> and the <hi>lowing of the ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en</hi> belied him. Your daily practiſes beare witneſſe, whether you be ſuch men as you call your ſelves.</p>
               <p n="3">3 You ſay that ye have <hi>ſuſpended your judgement and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe about things controverted, till they be determined by a lawfull aſſembly. Anſwer</hi> 1. You did not ſuſpend your judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and practiſe, but by your covenant have abjured theſe things controverted, <hi>as heads of poperie;</hi> as the learned Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors of <hi>Aberdeen</hi> moſt clearely have ſhowen, which yee were never hitherto able to anſwer: and if this bee to ſuſpend your judgement, you are worſe than the wife of <hi>Bodwell,</hi> who firſt ſpake, and then adviſed; you have firſt ſworne to the one part of the controverſie, and then take it to conſultation. 2. If we will grant you that ye have only ſuſpended your judgements and practiſe, &amp;c. conſider how abſurd you are herein: firſt, ye with an implicite faith ſweare to believe and practice what ſhall bee determined in a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full aſſembly, though ye know not, whether it ſhall approve or condemne thoſe things. 2 You fall head-long in another point of <hi>Poperie</hi> in making the generall aſſemblie an infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Iudge, at whoſe determination ye ſweare to ſtand, in judgemen and practice: for if yee did acknowledge that the aſſembly might erre, it had beene great folly in you to ſweare to ſtand to the determination of one, who is not of infallible judgement. 3. I demand of you who are the ſtrict <hi>Non-conformists.</hi> What if the aſſembly had determined con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:19621:12"/>to your expectation, and declare that thoſe things controverted were not <hi>heads of Popery,</hi> would ye have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcended to them? and if the aſſemblie had not been made up of <hi>conjured perſous,</hi> but of <hi>free Miniſters,</hi> it had beene ſo concluded.</p>
               <p>Your laſt two differences may be joyned in one, you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe your ſelves to be zealous in religion, and that the Kings Majeſtie is urging the ſwearing to the true religion of his Subjects, &amp;c. Who then is to hurt our religion? who is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming by armes to deſtroy it? if his Majeſtie be for you, who is againſt you? You have the King a <hi>Patterne and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron of Piety,</hi> and why did you proteſt againſt the covenant, becauſe hee commanded it? But all this tends to no other ſenſe then to brand ſo worthy a King with perjurie and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimulation.</p>
               <p>You have therefore moſt wickedly ſtared the queſtion, eſpecially ſince his Majeſtie by many publiſhed Proclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons hath often aſſured you, that he is ſo far from thinking of any innovation of religion, that he is reſolved conſtantly to maintaine the ſame, as it is eſtabliſhed by law in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and hath beene ſo ready to give all full ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, that he hath in a manner granted all that was pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titioned for of his Majeſtie: reade his Majeſties Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Declaration, dated the 27. of Febr. where ye ſhall finde the ſtate of the queſtion rightly ſet downe, and clearely ſee, that he is ſo farre from intending the ruine and ſubver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of this his Kingdome, that he takes God, and the world to witneſſe, that he is at laſt forced to take armes, and that for his owne right, and our good, to reclaime us from our daring and encreaſing inſolencies, and for the re-eſtabliſhing of his royall authority amongſt us againe. And therefore the queſtion is now, <hi>Whether he be our King or not?</hi> Yea, the queſtion muſt be now, not, <hi>Whether you may take defenſive armes againſt the King.</hi> But, <hi>Whether or no the Kings Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie may take defenſive armes againſt a diſloyall and rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous people:</hi> for doe not you invade his loyall ſubjects, beſieg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his cities by armies of men, becauſe they remaine obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:19621:13"/>and loyall to their King: have not you by force and fraud taken his Caſtles, led captive his captaines, and other ſubjects, and laid hold upon all whom ye know loyall ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, to ward them, and compell them to runne your croo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked courſe? you ſpare not the Lords owne Day, in time of Gods ſervice, in the houſe dedicated to his worſhip, to take his Majeſties ſervants and keepe them in ward, and diſpone upon the Kings forts and caſtles, as you thinke good; put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in and putting out whom you pleaſe: drinking and carouzing in his Caſtles, <hi>quaſi jam partâ victoriâ.</hi> I, you have triumphed, leading the Kings <hi>Crowne</hi> captive, with Tuck of Drumme, in great ſolemnitie through the ſtreet of your <hi>Citie of Confuſion:</hi> and afterward have not onely appointed your office-men of warre for reſiſting of authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, but alſo (as I am credibly informed) have erected a new government of 26. Governours of <hi>Nobles, Barons,</hi> and <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſſes</hi> yearely changeable, for the government of the Kingdome.</p>
               <p>As for his <hi>Supremacie</hi> then, no wonder that it be gon, for in your laſt pretended generall aſſembly, you are not far from that which <hi>Optatus</hi> ſayes of the <hi>Donatiſts, Ille ſolito furore accenſus, dicit, Quid imperatoricum eccleſia?</hi> he being kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with his wonted furie,<note place="margin">Contra Parm. lib. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> ſayes, <hi>What hath the Emperour to doe with the Church?</hi> In your proteſtations you give him no more a-doe, but to be preſent among you, that as an inferior officer he may attend you, and ſee that no tumult or outward diſorders be among you, who are the ſupreme Iudges in cauſes Eccleſiaſticall. You will admit of no appellation from you to the King, but have deprived them that thus appealed whilſt even the <hi>Iewes</hi> in an <hi>Eccleſiaſticall matter,</hi> admitted <hi>Pauls</hi> lawfull appeale to a Pagan Emperour:<note place="margin">Acts 25.11.</note> and whereas generall aſſemblies ſhould ever carrie <hi>libertatem judicandi, non neceſsitatem credendi,</hi> as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaies; and the acts thereof are only <hi>Canons,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Auguſt. contra Fauſt.</note> 
                  <hi>Directions,</hi> and <hi>Rules,</hi> without any power to be <hi>lawes,</hi> till they be confirmed, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and allowed by the <hi>Supreme Magiſtrate, Qui ſervit Chriſto, Leges ferendo pro Chriſto,</hi> who ſerve Chriſt, making Lawes
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:19621:13"/>for Chriſt, as <hi>Auguſtin</hi> ſaies, yet you make them to be lawes of <hi>coactive</hi> power, by vertue wherof, ye depoſe and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate whom you pleaſe, ſummon before your <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittees,</hi> whom and when you pleaſe; and becauſe they did not appeare before your <hi>Committee,</hi> though forbidden by his Majeſties Proclamation, they have ſuſpended them from their Miniſteriall function. Thus Attributing to their Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly not only <hi>Directive,</hi> but alſo <hi>Coactive power,</hi> not only without, but alſo againſt ſupreme Authority. It remaines then that ye conclude with <hi>Emanuell Sa</hi> in his Aphoriſme, <hi>Clericirebellio in regem, non eſt crimen laeſae Majeſtatis,</hi> The rebellion of Church-men againſt the King is no treaſon, <hi>quia non ſunt ſubditi regis,</hi> becauſe they are not ſubject to the King in Church matters. And that ye rob him of his <hi>Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy</hi> in matters civill, it will be cleare in the diſpute fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing: And therfore, notwithſtanding of all your ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious words that ye intend no change of Governement, <hi>ſcelera reclamant,</hi> and your proteſtations are <hi>contrariae factis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But if you will perſwade the people on the contrary, that his Majeſty intends the ruine of Church and policy, you muſt not thinke it enough to ſay it ſo boldly, but to make it good, or els how can ye eſcape the wrath of God? Who dare thus affirme of your King in Word, and <hi>Writ,</hi> in <hi>Pulpit,</hi> and <hi>elſ-where;</hi> againſt whom you ought not <hi>to thinke evill in your bed-chamber.</hi> And how can you eſcape <hi>the wrath of a King,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 16.14. &amp; 20.2.</note> 
                  <hi>which is as the Meſſenger of death, and as the roaring of a Lion? who ſo provoketh him to anger, ſinneth againſt his owne Soule.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But though it were ſo, that his Majeſty, who is the moſt religious King in Chriſtendome, were an enemy to religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and were by armes ſeeking that which you affirme he doth, can you ſhew any reaſon, why ye ought not to be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject unto him? Obedience is not to be given, but ſubjection muſt never be denied. I come then to your reaſons.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:19621:14"/>
               <head>Covenanter.</head>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>1.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Argument.</note> The firſt is taken from the unreaſonableneſſe and abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity of ſuch Court Paraſites, as for their own baſe ends maintain the abſolute Soveraignty, and unlimited autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of Princes, to the great hurt both of Prince and people, by looſing all the bonds of ciuill ſocieties, while the Prince, againſt the ſtrongest bands of oathes and lawes, may do what he pleaſe, to the ruine of Religion, the Kirk and Kingdom, the Lawes and liberties of ſome, or of all the Subjects, and the people ſhall do nothing, but either fly, which is impoſſible, or ſuffer themſelves to be maſſacred and out off.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Anticovenanter.</head>
               <p>You begin with <hi>unreaſonableneſſe</hi> and <hi>abſurdities,</hi> and ſo may you end: for all is abſurd, all is unreaſonable which you ſay. If any would have proponed this queſtion before this uprore came amongſt us, in <hi>Ahaſuerus</hi> words, <hi>Who is he? and where is he that durſt preſume in his heart to ſay ſo?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſter 7.5.</note> Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly we would never have dreamed, that ſuch a <hi>Cockatrice</hi> could be bred in the breſt of a <hi>Proteſtant:</hi> which doctrine is abominable even to many of the Jeſuites. I ſay of theſe ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments as <hi>Auguſtin</hi> did of the <hi>Donatiſts, In lucem traxiſſe, eſt viciſſe,</hi> To bring them to the light, is to overcome them. One <hi>Cherilus</hi> a Poet wrot a book of Poeſie, wherof all the verſes were faulty, except ſeven; for the which he received ſeven peeces of Gold; and for every evill verſe, which were many, he received one ſtripe. If your arguments were thus tryed and examined, for every argument ye would receive a ſtripe; and as the fault exceeds, ſo ſhould the puniſhment: but I wiſh you may not receive according to your demerits. If your reaſons were ſet down in Syllogiſmes their weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe would appeare; but we muſt anſwer as ye ſet them downe: firſt I deny that the Kings power is <hi>abſolute</hi> and <hi>unlimited</hi> in reſpect of God, who hath ſet ſuch Marches to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:19621:14"/>him that he ought not to <hi>tranſgreſſe:</hi> but in reſpect of men, the Kings power muſt be <hi>abſolute</hi> and <hi>unlimited,</hi> ſo that their ſubjects may not <hi>reſist them, but be ſubject unto them,</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Scripture.<note place="margin">Rom. 13.1</note> 
                  <hi>Let every ſoule be ſubject unto the higher powers: and he that reſiſteth reſisteth the ordinance of God.</hi> And that of <hi>Salomon, Eccleſ.</hi> 8. <hi>Where the word of a King is, there is power: and who may ſay unto him, What doeſt thou?</hi> To this purpoſe, <hi>Ambroſe in Enaraction. in Pſal.</hi> 51. ſaies on theſe words, <hi>Tibiſoli peccavi. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ti<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> rex erat, null is ipſe legibus tenebatur, quia liberi ſunt reges à vinculis deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorum, ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> enim ullis ad poenam vocantur legibus, tuti im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery poteſtate—ſed quamvis tutus, devotione tamen &amp; fide erat Deo ſubditus, &amp; legi ejus ſubjectum ſe eſſe cognoſcens, peccatum ſuum negare non poterat,</hi> That is, <hi>David</hi> ſaid, That he had ſinned againſt God, becauſe he was a King, and not bound to any law, <hi>becauſe Kings are free from the bonds of Crime, &amp;c.</hi> So ſaies <hi>Arnobius, Caſſiodorus, Beda, Gloſſa ordinar: Didimus, Cyrillus, Nicaetas in aurea catena:</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides all ſound modern <hi>Proteſtant Divines.</hi> So ſaies <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome</hi> alſo <hi>in Pſal.</hi> 118. <hi>Octon.</hi> 17. <hi>Rex etſi leges in poteſtate habet ut impunè delinquat, Deo tamen ſubditus eſt.</hi> Albeit the King have the Law ſo in his power, that he may ſin without controlement, yet he is ſubject to God: <hi>&amp; ſufficit illi in poenam quod Deum expectet ultorem.</hi> I hope they will not call theſe Authors Court Paraſites.</p>
               <p>Again, if their power were not abſolute, there would be ſome other power above them, which is abſurd, that the ſupreme power under God, can have any ſupreme power above it, but only God. <hi>Super Imperatorem non eſt niſi ſolus Deus, qui fecit Imperatorem,</hi> ſaies <hi>Optatus lib.</hi> 3. <hi>contra Parmeman.</hi> And therfore, <hi>in Synodo Regiaticana</hi> under <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorinus</hi> the Emperour, <hi>cap.</hi> 16. It's ſaid, <hi>Imperatores ſummi ac principes minimè nunc judicantur, ſed in futuro judicio à Deo.</hi> I conclude this point than with that grave ſaying of <hi>Yvo Carnotenſis Epiſcopus, Epist.</hi> 171. <hi>Si reges aliquando po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtate ſibi conceſſa abutantur, non ſunt à nobis graviter ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſperandi, ſed ubi ſacerdotum admonitionibus non acquieve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:19621:15"/>divino ſunt judicio reſervandi, ubi tanto diſtrictiùs ſunt puniendi, quanto minùs fuerint divinis admonitionibus obnoxy.</hi> What then is the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nreaſonableneſſe</hi> of this abſolute authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in reſpect of men? Great hurt, ſay you, both to <hi>Prince and people.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. It's no queſtion but great hurt may fall out both to Prince and people, while the Prince preſuming upon his authority, abuſeth the ſame, and makes himſelf liable to the wrath of God. But much more hurt would follow upon the other hand, if the <hi>Princes power</hi> were ſubject to the <hi>inferior ſubjects;</hi> that would breed great confuſion, and turn all up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide down, to make the <hi>Supreme</hi> under his <hi>Inferiours: everſe hoc ordine, publicae tanquilitatis nervum incidi, totam<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae ſocietatis compagem laxari, ac diſturbarineceſſe eſt,</hi> ſaies <hi>Tilen.</hi> When ever the ſubjects pleaſed they would be raiſing commotions and ſeditions, <hi>Corah, Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abiram</hi> would ſay,<note place="margin">Numb. 16.3.</note> 
                  <hi>You take too much upon you, Moſes. Abſalom</hi> would ſtrive to ſteal the hearts of the people away from the King. The Univerſity of <hi>Paris</hi> (though <hi>Papiſts</hi>) <hi>in Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſura lata. die</hi> 4. <hi>Iuny</hi> 1610. is of this ſame judgement, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling it <hi>Seditioſum, impium, ac haereticum, quocun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> quaeito colore à quocun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſubdito, vaſſallo, aut extraneo, ſacris Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gum ac Principum perſonis vim habere:</hi> A ſeditious, wicked and hereticall thing, that violence ſhould be offered to the ſacred perſons of Kings and Princes, upon whatſoever pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>texts or colour, by whoſoever, vaſſall, or forrainner. They ſay further, that it is a ſeditious doctrine, <hi>Regni optimates &amp; proceres ad foediſſimam deſertionem, populum ad generalem de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectionem at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſeditionem, ſpecioſo quidem, ſed fucato Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis Catholicae retinendae at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> conſervanda praetextu, hortans, excitans, impellans.</hi> A doctrine exhorting, ſtirring up, and thruſting forward the great men and Nobles of the Land to a moſt filthy deſertion, the people to a generall defection and ſedition, under a glorious indeed (but yet fained) pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text, of retaining and conſerving the Catholik religion. And therfore, I conclude with <hi>M. Geor. Froger in dicta Cenſura. Nè ſubjecti domino noſtre regi, abripi ſe ſinant affrice
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:19621:15"/>pestilentis iſtius dectrina vento.</hi> Let not the Subjects of our Soveraign Lord the King, ſuffer themſelves to be violently carried away with the Affrick wind of this peſtilent do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine. And finally, if there were ſuch power in the people above the Prince, the ſupreme Majeſty would be rather in the people, than in the Prince.</p>
               <p>But you ſay, if we reſiſt not, <hi>Church and ſtate will go to ruine. An</hi> 1. There is no danger to Church or Kingdome from his Majeſty, who is only to put away <hi>diſonders,</hi> and to reſtore the Church to her <hi>liberty.</hi> 2. Though there were ſuch dangers threatned, yet unlawfull means (ſuch as is the reſiſting ſuperiour powers) for good ends, ought not to be uſed, ſuffering is <hi>commanded</hi> and <hi>commended</hi> unto us in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, reſiſting is <hi>forbidden.</hi> By reſiſting, Tyrants are more <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged,</hi> by patient ſuffering, they are <hi>mitigated;</hi> reſiſting brings <hi>ruine</hi> to a Church, ſuffering cauſeth it to <hi>flouriſh;</hi> the bloud of the Saints is the <hi>ſeed</hi> of the Church: and it's obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the learned, that ſo long as the Churches in the primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive times uſed <hi>ſua arma,</hi> their own weapons, <hi>prayers</hi> and <hi>teares</hi> againſt the perſecuters, <hi>they flouriſhed:</hi> but when they took <hi>aliena arma,</hi> ſtrange armour, then they came to ruine; as it is this day under the dominion of the <hi>Turkes</hi> and <hi>Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels.</hi> It's well ſaid, that <hi>Peccata pepuli ſunt vires tyranno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> The ſins of the people are the ſtrength of tyrants: and therfore, when by patience, by teares, and ſupplicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons we ſeek God, God pardons our ſins, and our ſins be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing remooved, the ſtrength of Tyrants is abated: and God can put a hook in their mouth, and draw them back from perſecuting his Church. But when we reſiſt, we augment our ſins, and uſurpe <hi>Gods place,</hi> to whom only it belongs to take order with wicked Kings, ſince they have none above them, but God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Covenanter.</head>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2.</hi> From that line and order of ſubordination,<note place="margin">Argument.</note> wherin the Magiſtrate is placed under God the great Superiour, and the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:19621:16"/>Subjects are placed under God the Great, and under the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, the leſſe Superiour. When the Magiſtrate commands contrary to God, and goeth out of his order and line, eſpecially ſo farr as to invade by armes, if they obey not; the ſubjects keeping of their own line and order, and defending themſelves, is not diſobedience to the Magiſtrate, but obedience to God, who in this point, ſo long as the Magiſtrate runneth this courſe, becomes their immediate Superiour. And as under the Magiſtrate they ought to defend themſelves from all violence without: ſo in this abuſe of God and his ordinance, from all vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence within; otherwiſe, they ſin againſt God and their own ſoules. One inferiour officer ought to keep his own ſtation in the army, even when the Captain goeth out of his line and order, and taketh part with the enemy; and in this caſe, is bound no leſſe than before under his Coronell or Generall, to fight for himſelf, and for the ſafety of the whole army, againſt his own Captain. It were against ſenſe and reaſon to ſay, that he must give his neck to the ſword of the Captaine, without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of his Generall, the whole army, and his own life.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Anticovenanter.</head>
               <p>This Argument is not ſo ſpecious, as falſe; no man doubts, but when the Magiſtrate goeth out of his order, and by Armes commands, what God forbids; that, in that caſe, man is not tied to obedience. But to take up armes to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt, is the point in queſtion, which you call <hi>obedience to God,</hi> and not <hi>diſobedience to the Magiſtrate;</hi> but you beg the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, and cannot prove it, except from that, that God forbids to <hi>reſiſt ſuperiour Powers.</hi> 2. You deny the King, in this caſe to be your <hi>Superiour,</hi> ſo long as he commands contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to Gods Commandement; and God only becommeth your <hi>immediate Superiour:</hi> before this time, I never heard ſo much ſeditious and treaſonable doctrine. Did ever a Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit ſay ſo much? This juſtifieth their doctrine, for they hold, that, though Kings were never ſo wicked Tyrants, yet till the Pope declare them incapable of Authority, they remaine their lawfull Superiours: and if the falſe ground
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:19621:16"/>of this doctrine were true, to wit, that the Pope is above Kings, their doctrine even ſo farr were good. But that <hi>inferiours</hi> ſhould by their own <hi>uſurped authority</hi> and inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency diſclaime their <hi>Superiours,</hi> making God their only <hi>immediate Superiour</hi> is a moſt brutiſh doctrine, not worthy to be anſwered with words. As God ſometimes ſets up Kings to be nurſing fathers to the Church, (as long may it be, we have one) ſo ſomtime he will raiſe wicked men to be a ſcourge to his Church: to both theſe, we ought <hi>obedience</hi> in all things lawfull; and <hi>ſubjection,</hi> when obedience is not lawfull, and never diſclaime their authority. So the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians under <hi>Iulian</hi> the Apoſtate fought his battels, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed him, when he commanded things lawfull: but when he commanded things unlawful they did not obey, &amp; yet ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver reſiſted (though powerful to reſiſt) but were ever in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection to their temporal Lord, for their eternal Lords ſake. So ſayes <hi>Auguſtin</hi> in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 124. <hi>Quando volebat ut idola co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerent, ut thurificarent, praeponebant illi Deum: quando au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem dicebat, producite aciem, ite contra illam gentem, ſtatim obtemperabant, diſtinguebant Dominum aeternum a Domino temporali, tamen ſubditi erant propter Dominum aeternum, etiam Domino temporali.</hi> That which you cannot prove by reaſon, you would proove by a ſimilitude of a Captain and his Souldiers, but you know that 1. <hi>Theologia ſymbolica non eſt argumentativa.</hi> 2. The compariſon is not alike, but hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth down-right: for the authority of the Captain is <hi>limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> and <hi>bounded</hi> by his Prince or Generall, that he muſt not tranſgreſſe in the leaſt point of his <hi>Commiſſion;</hi> otherwiſe the ſouldiers are no more bound to follow him, then they know his Commiſſion from their common Prince. As for example, the King of <hi>France</hi> ſends his armies to fight againſt the <hi>Spaniards:</hi> Now, if the Captain of this army make de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection from the King, and go to the Spaniſh army, then they become as <hi>Spaniards,</hi> enemies to their own King; now here ſenſe it ſelfe leads the army to fight againſt their Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, who are turned enemies; for they certainly know, that it was the Kings will to fight againſt the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:19621:17"/>all that would take their part in that battell, and therfore they haue their Kings warrant to fight againſt their cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, who now <hi>ipſo facto</hi> ceaſeth to be their captaine, and become enemies. But if the King did give theſe his Captains abſolute and unlimited power over the armies, comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the ſouldiers not to reſiſt them by armes, whither they did right or wrong; whither they ſhould turn to the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my or not; in this caſe indeed as the ſouldiers ought not to turne away after them to the enemy againſt their Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne, ſo they ought not to fight againſt them; but fly home to their Prince, whoſe will they know. Thus ſtands the caſe between God and the King his Deputy, God hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him ſuch authority, that all under him muſt be <hi>ſubject</hi> unto him without reſiſtance; and though he ſhould doe many things contrary to Gods Word, yet <hi>ipſo facto</hi> he cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth not to be King, and we muſt not obey him in evill, but yet be <hi>ſubject</hi> unto him for Conſcience ſake.</p>
               <p>The Covenanters ſeeing the weakneſſe of this their argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and the ſtrength of reaſon againſt it from the Apoſtles Direction, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1. they ſtrive (but unhappily) to anſwer that objection, thus.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Covenanter.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>It's objected</hi> Rom. <hi>13.1.</hi> Let every ſoule be ſubject unto the higher powers. <hi>Anſwer.</hi> Tyranny and unjuſt violence is not the ordinance of God, and he that reſisteth it, reſiſts not the ordinance of God: they are rulers contrary to good workes, not to evill, they are not the Miniſters of God for good, neither in this can we be ſubject unto them for conſcience ſake. The whole courſe of the Apoſtles argument runneth againſt the reſiſtance of lawfull power, commanding things good and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full; We muſt either acknowledge Tyranny to be the ordinance of God, and for our good, or els exclude it from the Apostles argument, admitting the reſiſtance therof to be lawfull, at leaſt by the ſhield for defence, if not by the ſword for invaſion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:19621:17"/>
               <head>Anticovenanter.</head>
               <p>In this you declare either much weakneſſe, or elſe much malice; and I may ſay both. No man will affirme that <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannie</hi> and <hi>violence</hi> are Gods ordinance, but thoſe to whom God hath given lawfull authority, may abuſe it <hi>tyrannically;</hi> and they remaine the Miniſters of God for thy good, <hi>in tuum bonum</hi> (ſaies <hi>Auguſtin</hi>) <hi>licet ſibi in malum:</hi> for all things work together for the beſt to them that love God. For the Lord will raiſe up <hi>Kings</hi> ſometimes (as <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſaies) to be <hi>The rod of his anger and ſtaffe of his indignation,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſai. 10 5.</note> 
                  <hi>to afflict an hypocriticall people, to take the ſpoyle and the prey, and to tread them downe like the mire in the ſtreets: Howbeit he meaneth not ſo, neither doth his heart thinke ſo,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>but it is in his heart to deſtroy nations, not a few.</hi> And when tyrants thinke thus to doe evill to us, yet it turneth to <hi>our good</hi> to humble us under Gods hand, and cauſe us repent. <hi>This is all the fruit, to take away our iniquity,</hi> ſaith the Lord:<note place="margin">Iſai. 27 9.</note> and thus, <hi>Tyranni ſunt miniſtri Dei tibi in bonum, licet ſibi in malum:</hi> and to reſiſt them is to fight with God, and pull the rod out of his hand. Your inference then is moſt chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh, that <hi>either we muſt admit tyrannie to be Gods ordinance, or elſe we may reſiſt it.</hi> For you ſee that he who hath a lawfull power from God, may abuſe it tyrannically, and we muſt not reſiſt Gods ordinance, lawfull authority; becauſe ſuch and ſuch men exerciſe it tyrannically. Our ſuperiors power is not <hi>Gods ordinance,</hi> becauſe he is a <hi>good man</hi> that hath it, as <hi>David</hi> was: neither is the authority, not Gods ordinance, becauſe he is an <hi>evill man</hi> that hath it, as <hi>Saul</hi> was: but the authority is Gods ordinance, becauſe he who hath it, is the <hi>lawfull ſuperior.</hi> He that was Emperour, when <hi>Paul</hi> writ this Epiſtle, was <hi>Nero,</hi> a tyrant. <hi>Nero</hi> (ſayes lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Moulin</hi>) <hi>was a monſter in nature, the ſhame of humane kinde, and the firſt Emperour that began to perſecute the Church, nevertheleſſe the Apostle,</hi> Rom. 13. <hi>ſpeaking of that power which then was in being, ſaith, that it was ordained by
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:19621:18"/>God, and that whoſever reſiſted the ſame, reſiſted the ordinance of God,</hi> &amp;c. So ſayes <hi>Aug. De civit Dei lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 21. Where he declares that the authority of wicked Emperours <hi>was from Gods ordinance,</hi> as well as of good Emperours, <hi>Qui Mario, Caio, Caeſari, qui Auguſto ipſe &amp; Neroni; qui Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaſianis, vel patri vel filio ſuaviſſimis imperatoribus, ipſe &amp; Domitiano crudeliſſimo: &amp; ne per ſingulos ire neceſſe ſit, qui Conſtantino Chriſtiano, ipſe &amp; apoſtatae Iuliano.</hi> Did not <hi>Paul</hi> acknowledge the authority of <hi>Nero, when he did ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale to him,</hi> and that lawfully, <hi>I ſtand at Caeſars judgement ſeat, where I ought to be judged:</hi> Act. 25.10. And Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe acknowledged the Authority of <hi>Pilate</hi> over him to be from above. Neither was it lawfull for Chriſts Diſciples to reſiſt, and by armes to defend their Maſter againſt ſuch matchleſſe cruelty and tyrannie.</p>
               <p>And here by the way, I gather one argument againſt your courſe, which I pray you anſwer. It was not lawfull for Chriſts Diſciples to defend Chriſt by armes againſt the tyranny of thoſe who invaded him, and crucified him. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, its not lawfull for us to take deſenſive armes againſt ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants. Ye will anſwer, Chriſt ſuffered them not to reſiſt, becauſe it was his will to ſuffer. This is true indeed, he was moſt willing to ſuffer, but yet the reaſon wherefore he hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders <hi>Peter</hi> to defend him, is, becauſe it <hi>was not lawfull</hi> for him to defend by armes, therefore he ſayes, <hi>Put up thy ſword into his place, for he that takes the ſword ſhall periſh with the ſword.</hi> He that drawes the ſword, muſt doe it by the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of him that hath power.</p>
               <p>Conſider alſo the 13. Chap. of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> in the 7 ver. It's ſaid, that the beaſt with the ſeven heads and ten hornes <hi>had power given him over all kinreds, tongues, and nations, to make war with the Saints.</hi> What ſhall the Saints doe then un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their perſecuters? May they not take up armes? Nor, for in the next words, the Spirit of God ſets down the manner of the Saints defence <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: Firſt, tels what muſt not be done, and then what they muſt doe; firſt, they muſt not reſiſt, and take their perſecuters either captive,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:19621:18"/>or kill them, becauſe they have not that power; therefore ſayes the Text, <hi>He that leadeth in captivity, ſhall goe into captivity; he that killeth with the ſword, ſhall be killed with the ſword,</hi> then he ſheweth that they muſt ſuffer. <hi>Here is the patience and faith of the Saints,</hi> ſayes the Text. <hi>Patience</hi> is requiſite to endure tribulation, and <hi>faith,</hi> to continue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant to the end. I pray you conſider this my Brethren of the Miniſtery, and be not the kindlers of this unlawfull war againſt not a Tyrant, but the moſt religious Prince in the world. <hi>An evill man ſeeketh only rebellion;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 17.11.</note> 
                  <hi>therfore a cruell meſſenger ſhall be ſent unto him,</hi> ſayes <hi>Salomon,</hi> Remember <hi>Bernards</hi> ſaying, <hi>Epiſt</hi> 134. <hi>Non eſt meum hortar, ad pugnam. Est tamen (ſecurus dic) advocati eccleſiae arcere ab eccleſiae infestatione Schiſmaticorum rabiem, est Caeſaris propriam vindicare coronam ab uſurpatore Siculo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Finally, You make it queſtionable, whether you may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade Tyrants or not, <hi>at least by the ſhield of defence, if not by the ſword; for invaſion,</hi> ſay you, not determining what may be done: and therefore, you ſhew too much choler to call it a <hi>divelliſh and diſpitefull calumnie of diſnatured enemies, if they make the queſtion about invaſion of his Majeſties King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes.</hi> Your irreſolution in this queſtion, <hi>at leaſt, if not,</hi> is reſolved by your practice who are the invaders, and our Gratious King muſt be the defender. The author of the <hi>Dialogue of white divelt,</hi> goeth clearly to work, affirming, if Kings hinder the bringing in of their Diſcipline, they are Tyrants, and being Tyrants, they may be depoſed by their Subjects: and do not you maintaine that the Kings autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and true Religion are ſo firmely joyned together, that if he fall from his Religion he falleth alſo from his authority; and ſo is no more your King when you judge him contrary to Religion by common conſent; neither are you more bound to him, then he defends the true Religion, that is, which you think the true Religion.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:19621:19"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:19621:19"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:19621:20"/>
               <head>Covenanter.</head>
               <p>From the end of magiſtracie,<note place="margin">3. Argument.</note> the Lord hath ordained Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates to be his miniſters for the good of his people; whence have proceeded theſe principles of Policie, Princes are principally for the people and their defence, and not the people principally for them; the ſafety and good of the people is the ſupreme Law, magistracie is the inferiour and ſubordinate law, the people make the Magiſtrate, but the Magiſtrate maketh not the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; the people may be without the Magiſtrate, for the world was governed in another way, till that <hi>Cain</hi> building a Citie, made the godly firſt take this order for their defence, the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate cannot be without the people; the body of the Magiſtrate is mortall, the body of the people immortall: and therfore, it were a direct overturning of all the foundation of policie and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment to preferre ſubjection to the Prince, to the preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Common-wealth, or to expoſe the publike, wherein every mens perſon, family and private eſtate is contained, to be a prey to the furie of the Prince, rather than by all our power to defend and preſerve the Common-wealth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Anticovenanter.</head>
               <p>There is nothing here but moſt odious and contemptible words againſt the Authority of our <hi>ſupreme Magiſtrate,</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerring <hi>the people</hi> by many degrees above the <hi>Prince.</hi> I ſay with <hi>Bernard,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">De conſider. lib <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Situr ques Deus conjunxit, non ſunt ſeparandi, ſione<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s ſubju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>it comparandit mouſtrum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>movens digitam facis peudere de capite.</hi> You doe not ſo, you ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate the King and Subjects whom God hath conjoyned, and you compare the people who are ſubjoyned to the Prince, farre above the Prince. But I come to examine the particulars. You ſay well, that God hath <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Princes for the good of his people,</hi> but what gather ye hence, that ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the people may take up armes? that is a ſtrange conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent: Certainly, if the Prince faile in the doing what God
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:19621:20"/>commandeth, God his <hi>Maſter</hi> will take order with him; and not the people, whom you here make the Kings Maſter. The Scripture tells us,<note place="margin">Rom. 13.4.</note> That he is the <hi>Miniſter of God for thy good,</hi> but with your leave, he muſt be <hi>your Commander,</hi> and not one of <hi>your creatures,</hi> your <hi>Miniſter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2 You ſay <hi>Princes are principally for the people,</hi> and <hi>not the people for the Prince. Anſ.</hi> You ſhould ſay, for <hi>[people]</hi> ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, if you doe not diſdaine to be called Subjects. Now the King and Subjects are relative, and they are for other; the one to <hi>Command and governe,</hi> the other to be <hi>ſubject and led.</hi> Now what is all this for reſiſting of authority?</p>
               <p n="3">3 You ſay, The <hi>good of the people is the ſupreme Law,</hi> &amp;c. This is the ſecond time that you have ignorantly abuſed that ſaying, <hi>Salus populi ſuprema lex eſto,</hi> Goe to the learned Doctors of <hi>Aberdeen,</hi> and learne out of their <hi>Duplies</hi> the meaning of it. It belongeth to the Magiſtrate, who is the onely <hi>Law giver.</hi> The caſe may fall out, that for the good of his Subjects, he muſt not ſtand upon the ordinary Law, but let that ſtand for a Law, which in ſuch exigence ſhall ſee me to him fitteſt for the ſafety of the people: But you odiouſly apply it to the people, who are deſtitute of authority, and can make no law. Let the people ſee what is moſt condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible for their owne ſafety, though it ſhould be with the loſſe of the ſupreme Magiſtrate; let him periſh rather then his Subjects: as who would ſay, rather then let the <hi>members</hi> of the body ſuffer ſuch hazzard, out off the <hi>Head.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4 Ye ſay <hi>the people makes the Magiſtrate, &amp;c.</hi> You de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare now what people you are (for ye will not call your ſelves Subjects) even great enemies to <hi>Monarchs.</hi> Is your doctrine ſo Jeſuiticall and rebellious, to thinke that the Kings authority is of humane inſtitution by poſitive lawes, and not from God? if you ſay ſo, Treply with <hi>Bernard, Si ſie ſontis, diſſentis ab co qui dicit, non eſt poteſtas niſi a Deo.</hi> We have maintained this doctrine too long againſt the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary, to paſſe from it now upon your naked word with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out probation. It's the <hi>Lord that places Kings in their throne,</hi> ſaies <hi>Iob.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Job 36.7. Prov. 8.15.</note> 
                  <hi>By me Kings raigne, ſaies the Wiſedome of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:19621:21"/>God. Non tribuamus dands regni atque imperij poteſtatem, niſi Deo vero. Auguſt.</hi> Theſe cannot properly be called <hi>Kings,</hi> who have their power from the people, becauſe <hi>publike Governement</hi> is onely proper to God, who giveth it to whom he pleaſeth. And ſeeing it is contrary to reaſon, that any can have <hi>ſupreme power</hi> over <hi>himſelfe;</hi> it followeth that the people wanting a King cannot have the <hi>ſupreme power</hi> over it ſelfe; and therefore cannot beſtow it upon any man to be their King, for none can give that to another which they have not themſelves.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Ye ſay <hi>the people may be without the Magiſtrate. Anſwer.</hi> So have you made us this yeare and more; in ſtead of a King. we have had the <hi>Ephori</hi> of <hi>Sparta,</hi> and the Roman Tribunes over-ruling us, ſtrange Lords rule over us to the great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of our own King. <hi>Dominis parere ſuperbis, cogimur.</hi> 2. The world was not without a King till <hi>Cain's</hi> time: for <hi>Adam</hi> was King, his Empire was paternall, and therfore Monarchicall; for albeit, at firſt he did not actually exerciſe politicall Government before the people did multiply; yet <hi>ex vijuris naturae,</hi> by the force of the law of nature, it was due to the firſt progenitor <hi>Adam,</hi> to be governour of his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity, and thus <hi>habitually,</hi> he was King from his firſt crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: and therfore that aſſertion of the <hi>Monarchomachiſts</hi> is not alwaies true, <hi>the King is not without a people, as the people are without a King.</hi> I ſee, you think you may be well without our King, what remaineth then, but with the <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops,</hi> let <hi>Kings</hi> go too, and lay a ground for <hi>Anabaptiſme.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. You ſay the <hi>body of the Magiſtrate is mortall.</hi> I pray you what kind of people are you? <hi>Qui genus, unde demo?</hi> Are you only the off-ſpring of God? I reade in Scripture that God ſaies to Kings,<note place="margin">Pſal. 82.6, 7.</note> 
                  <hi>I have ſaid ye are gods,</hi> but to which of you is this name given? and if you will aſſume that to you, take the reſt of the Text with you, -<hi>but ye ſhall die like men.</hi> It's an old ſaying, <hi>Rex nunquam maritur,</hi> The King never dieth. But one generation goeth, and another com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth; Let it content you that tho King and you are of one mettall.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:19621:21"/>
Now in the end, having thus many waies preferred your ſelves to the King, you make this monſtrous concluſion. It's adirect over-turning of all foundation of Policie, to preferre ſubjection to the Prince, to the preſervation of the common-wealth. <hi>Anſw.</hi> Here you ſeparate that which God hath joyned together, and make theſe two oppoſite, which ever muſt go hand in hand together: for Subjection to the Prince, is the only way to preſerve the Common-wealth: where Subjection is not, Gods ordinance is contemned, the foundation of policie over-turned, and the Common-wealth expoſed to ruine, as is cleare in the anſwer to your firſt Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Covenanter.</head>
               <p>From the Covenant betwixt God and the people,<note place="margin">4. Argument.</note> for the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and the Magiſtrate are joyntly bound in Covenant with God, for obſerving and preſerving the Commandements of the firſt and ſecond tables, as may be ſeene in the bookes of <hi>Samuel, Kings,</hi> and <hi>Chronicles:</hi> As the fault of the people will not excuſe the Magiſtrates negligence, ſo the fault of the King will not excuſe the people, if they reſiſt not his violence, preſſing them againſt the Covenant of God, this argument is ſtrongly preſſed by ſound and religious politicians.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Anticovenanter.</head>
               <p>You ſhould declare, how King and people are both joint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bound: Will you have King and Subject of equall power, about the obſervation and preſervation of the Tables? You are bound to keep the Commandements of God, as well as your King; but the King is bound to do more, to wit, to be carefull, that all his Subjects keep them, and to puniſh tranſgreſſours. I have read the whole Scripture of God, but I could never find this power given to Subjects. It's enough for them to keep the Tables themſelves, but they have no authority to command others, much leſſe doth it belong to
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:19621:22"/>them to reſiſt the Magiſtrate. If the King preſſe the people to the breach of the Law, they muſt not obey; ſince God, his Superiour, commands the contrary; but yet they muſt not reſiſt, ſince God, both their Superiours, forbids. You poore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beg here the queſtion, affirming, that the people will ſin if they reſiſt not, but you will never prove it. You ſay, it is ſtrongly preſſed by ſound politicians, but you preſſe it moſt weakly and unfoundly, not nominating one ſound Politici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an for you. For no Wiſeman will confound the Princes authority with the people, and turne a <hi>Monarchie</hi> into a <hi>Democracie.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Covenanter.</head>
               <p>From the ſubordination of Powers appointed by God.<note place="margin">5. Argument.</note> The ſame law and order that appoints to obey the ſupreme Magiſtrate, rather than his Deputie, appoints us alſo to obey God, rather than man: and the ſame law and order that leadeth us to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the ſupreme Magiſtrate againſt the invaſion of his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putie, commandeth us alſo to defend Gods right, and to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the peoples peace againſt the unjuſt invaſion of the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Magiſtrate: who can be thought no leſſe ſubordinate to God, then his Vicegerent is to him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Anticovenanter.</head>
               <p>This Argument is builded upon ſand, you dreame, that whatſoever meanes may be uſed for preſervation of the Prince againſt his Deputies, the ſame may be uſed for the preſervation of Gods right, and the peoples peace. <hi>But you erre, not knowing the Scriptures, nor the power of God.</hi> Both by Gods Law, and mans law, <hi>Subjects</hi> are bound to defend their <hi>Prince.</hi> But Gods Law commands not to defend his right by <hi>armes:</hi> the weapons of our warfare are <hi>ſpirituall,</hi> and not <hi>carnall. Patience, Faith,</hi> with other graces, are our Armour, we muſt be ſubject for <hi>conſcience ſake,</hi> and not <hi>take Gods place</hi> to repreſſe our Superiours. If any inferiour judge
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:19621:22"/>wrong me, I muſt not reſiſt him, but appeale to his Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, and from him again, to his Superiour, even to the King the Supreme; and if he will be unjuſt, and wrong me, I muſt not reſiſt, but commit my cauſe to God, to whom venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance belongeth. It is a point of Atheiſme, and diſtruſting of Gods providence, to think that God will not help againſt Tyrants; and therfore men will be their owne judges, and revenge themſelves. But the Lord hath ſaid.<note place="margin">Pſal. 12.5.</note> 
                  <hi>For the oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the poore, and the ſighing of the needy, now I will ariſe, and ſet him in ſafety, &amp;c.</hi> Then take <hi>Salomons</hi> counſell, <hi>Prov.</hi> 20.22 <hi>Say not thou, I will recompenſe evill: but wait on the Lord, and he will ſave thee.</hi> Suffer me then to atteſt you, my deare Countrey-men. What thinke you to doe, <hi>O yee Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venanters,</hi> for God and the King? You undertake armes, not for God, who deſires nothing but peace: You publiſh Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, He commands Obedience. You trouble the reſt and quiet of a King, he willeth us to endure hardneſſe, though at the hand of a Pagan. You doe it for God, whoſe name yee call upon, and deny his Power. You doe it for God, who deteſteth your actions, and knowes your thoughts. And you doe it for that God, who will confound all thoſe who breed confuſion among his people. You undertake warre for Religion, againſt the Defender of Religion: You raiſe armies for Religion, and nothing hindereth it ſo much as warres: You fight for holineſſe, and your weapons de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the Church, authorize blaſphemie, plant Atheiſme, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety, and deſpiſing of Devotion in all places. You march under pretence of Religion, and you ſpoyle the Clergie of Tithes, Stipend, burden the Kings Subjects with impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, ranſack the Kings houſes. Pardon me, I pray you, to tell you, that this fortreſſe which you build, will be your overthrow; this fire you kindle, will burne you; theſe wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons ye forge, will be tempered in your own intrails; and that thereby you will neither leave of your ſelves, nor your Covenant ought, but a ſhamefull memory.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:19621:23"/>
               <head>Covenanter.</head>
               <p>If a private man be bound by the Law of nature to defend himſelf <hi>cum moderamine inculpatae turelae,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">6. Argument.</note> againſt the Prince or Iudge, as a private man invading him by violence, and not purſuing him judicially, and by order of law, and may repell violence with violence. If a chaſte Matron may defend her owne body, that it be not defiled by the Adulterer, were his place never ſo great. If children may reſiſt the violent invaſion of their parents againſt themſelves, their mother, or others of the family, notwithſtanding the ſtrict obligation betweene pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents and children. If ſervants may hold the hands of their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, ſeeking to kill them in their rage. If the Marriners and paſſengers may ſave themſelves by reſiſting him who ſits at the helm, and would drive the Ship against a rocke, or by hindering the Prince himſelfe, not only by ſupplication of mouth, but by ſtrength of hand, to miſ governe the ſhip to their certaine Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wracke, much more may the body defend it ſelf againſt all inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſion whatſoever.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Anticovenanter.</head>
               <p>You are put to poore ſhifts, when for arguments you bring crooked compariſons, yet good enough for ignorants. As for your firſt ſuppoſition, the queſtion is not, whether a private man may defend himſelf againſt his Superiour with <hi>inculpata tutela:</hi> But whether or not, defence by armes be <hi>culpata</hi> or <hi>inculpata tutela?</hi> His Majeſty denieth you not lawful defence by Law, but your taking up of armes to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt his Authority is damnable.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Tell me, when doth a Prince become a private man? as the Popes <hi>infallibility</hi> is left in his <hi>Chaire,</hi> ſo you make the Kings <hi>authority</hi> to reſide in his <hi>Throne:</hi> When <hi>Saul</hi> was in the wilderneſſe perſecuting <hi>David</hi> with great vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, was he then <hi>a private man?</hi> you will have it ſo; But I truſt <hi>David</hi> better then you all, who would not defend
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:19621:23"/>himſelfe by armes, but fled from him, as from the <hi>Lords A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed:</hi> who can touch the Lords Anointed, and be innocent? It is altogether againſt the Law of Nature, that <hi>private men</hi> ſhould take armes againſt their <hi>Superiors,</hi> ſeeing it's againſt the Law of nature, that a <hi>privat man</hi> ſhould be judge in his <hi>own</hi> cauſe, as <hi>Luther</hi> learnedly diſputes in the 5. book of <hi>Slei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens</hi> Commentaries.</p>
               <p>Your ſecond ſuppoſition is as idle. It becommeth a chaſt woman to defend her <hi>Chaſtity,</hi> even againſt the <hi>King,</hi> but how I pray you by taking up of <hi>armes?</hi> not at all, but by not yeelding her ſelfe into his <hi>armes:</hi> and though he being ſtronger than ſhe, force her; yet ſhe hath defended her <hi>cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtity,</hi> and only the <hi>King</hi> is the adulterer. Thus in (<hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtints</hi> judgement) <hi>Lucretia,</hi> that chaſte Matron, loſt not her <hi>Chaſtity,</hi> albeit <hi>Tarquinius</hi> the Emperour by force lay with her, only ſhe drew no ſword to reſiſt his violence; but here was her lamentable fault, that the fact, ſore againſt her will, being done, ſhe took armes againſt her ſelf, and killed her ſelfe.</p>
               <p>Your third ſuppoſition is no better, for there is no Law that authorizeth Children to reſiſt their Parents by armes. 2. Rules of prudency cannot be ſet down for every circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance; therfore in ſuch caſes, prudency will find out law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full means either to pacifie, or at leaſt to eſcape by flight, the parents fury. 3. If the caſe were ſo that either the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent muſt kill the child, or the child kill the Father, I think it becommeth the child, who hath his being of the Father, rather to <hi>ſuffer,</hi> than to <hi>deſtroy</hi> the fountain, whence he ſprang. 4. Parents have not ſo great power over their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, as Kings over their Subjects, Kings have power of <hi>life</hi> and <hi>death,</hi> which Parents have not. And your fourth compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon is yet more weak: for the maſters power over the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, is leſſe than Parents over their children.</p>
               <p>Your laſt ſuppoſition is true in part, <hi>the Mariners and Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers may reſiſt the Pilot,</hi> for <hi>Pilots</hi> are not <hi>Kings</hi> over the reſt in the ſhip: you do too baſely eſteem of Authority. But what if the King will drive the ſhip on the rock him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf?
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:19621:24"/>
                  <hi>Anſwer</hi> 1. By doing of this the King is no more ſeeking the <hi>ruine</hi> of the Marriners and Paſſengers, then his <hi>own aeſtruction,</hi> and in this caſe they are bound to ſave their King from death, in ſuch ſubmiſſive and humble manner as it becommeth, and not by <hi>armes,</hi> with <hi>ſwords, muſquets, pikes</hi> and <hi>Cannons,</hi> which are moſt offenſive weapons. 2. If the King would be thus deſperate, it cannot be but he is gone mad, and quite out of his wits, and ſo <hi>interpretativè,</hi> they have a warrant to hinder him to undo all, which he wil allow when he commeth to himſelf again. Well, al this may be done without taking of armes.</p>
               <p>But then ſay ye, may not the Church defend it ſelf from ſuffering ſhipwrack againſt a Tyrant, who is ſeeking that? <hi>Anſwer.</hi> It cannot be ſo done, the compariſon is much unlike. You ſpeak as if the one caſe were as obuious to the ſenſe as the other. They muſt be <hi>apparant</hi> rocks, not <hi>ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed</hi> only. Both ſenſe and reaſon tell that if the Prince be not hindered by the Mariners, he and all muſt periſh. But the Church of Chriſt, which is builded on a Rock, againſt the which all Tyrants violence, no, nor the gates of hell cannot prevaile, is a gainer by ſuffering, and every drop of their blood begets new believers: and ſo <hi>reſiſting,</hi> being an unlawfull meanes, may bring ruine to the Church, but <hi>ſuffering</hi> not ſo. If the Jewes in the daies of <hi>Ahaſverus</hi> had been of this new Scottiſh humor, when an utter extirpation was intended by <hi>Haman</hi> both of themſelves and their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, they would have taken armes; but their prayers and teares were their defence in their greateſt extremity. This was the conſtant practice of the Primitive Church alſo, even when they were moſt able to defend themſelves againſt their perſecutors: to this purpoſe <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi> expoſition on <hi>Pſal.</hi> 147. ſaith well, that God compaſſeth his Church with the croſſe, to ſuffer; not with wals for defence <hi>Eccleſiam (in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit) muniſt validius quàm Ieruſalem non vectibus &amp; por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, ſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eruce circumſeptam, &amp; renunciatione propria volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis, cùm dixis, Porta inferorum non pravalebant adverſm <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. In principio ita<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eges &amp; Imperatores, &amp; populi, &amp; ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitates,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:19621:24"/>&amp; damonum phalanges, &amp; ipſa diaboli Tyrannis, &amp; alia innumerabilia invaſerunt Eccleſiaem; illa tamen omnia fracta &amp; diſſoluia ſunt, &amp; interierunt, ipſa tamen crevit, &amp; in'tantam provect a est altitudinem, ut ipſos etiam coelos ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raverit.</hi> For God hath guarded his Church more ſtrongly then Jeruſalem, not being environed with gates and barrs, but with the <hi>croſſe,</hi> and the denyall of her ſelf, when he ſaid <hi>The gates of hell ſhall not prevaile againſt her.</hi> Therfore in the beginning, Kings and Emperours, people and cities, troups of Divels, yea and the very Tyranny of Satan, inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Church: yet all theſe things were undone and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved and periſhed; but the Church increaſed, in ſo much that ſhe reached unto the heavens, and all this was by ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring; for as the Arke of <hi>Noah,</hi> the more the floods increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the nearer it was to Heaven, ſo the more the Church is toſſed with the waves of affliction, the nearer it goeth to Heaven.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Covenanter.</head>
               <p n="7">
                  <hi>7.</hi> From Examples in Scripture, <hi>1.</hi> Sam. <hi>14 45.</hi> &amp; <hi>2.</hi> Chr,<note place="margin">7. Argument</note> 
                  <hi>26.17.2.</hi> Kings <hi>11.1.</hi> Sam. <hi>23.</hi> Where Davia bath ſix hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereth men for his defence againſt the King himſelf, and would have kept <hi>Keilah</hi> againſt him, neither himſelf nor the Prieſt doubting of the lawfullnes therof, only ſuſpecting the treachery of the <hi>Keilites.</hi> Examples of the reformed Kirks in Germany, the Low-countries, Sweden, and the Examples of our own Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Anticovenanter.</head>
               <p>It's a token that you put ſmall confidence in Scripture: becauſe you have not begun with it; but left it in the end. For certainly there is nothing here to prove your tenet. All your teſtimonies are out of the Old Teſtament, but not one out of the New Teſtament. What if I would grant it lawful under the Law, and that your teſtimonies are good for your
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:19621:25"/>purpoſe? but can ye ſhew it lawfull under the Goſpell, where ſuffering is only commanded?<note place="margin">Mat. 10.23.</note> 
                  <hi>When they perſecute you in one city, fly to another:</hi> not go take the cities and caſtles of your periecuting Superiours, and defend your ſelves. But as there is no help for you from the New Teſtament, ſo you ſhall have none from the Old Teſtament, as ſhall be cleare in anſwering your teſtimonies. In your firſt teſtimony, the people hindered <hi>Saul</hi> to kill <hi>Ionathan:</hi> but how did they it? Not by <hi>armes,</hi> but by <hi>entreary with ſound reaſons. Shall Ionathan die,</hi> ſay they, <hi>who hath wrought this great ſalvation in Iſrael? God forbid.</hi> But you will ſay, they oppoſed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in contradictory termes, ſaying, <hi>as the Lord liveth, there ſhall not one haire of his head fall to the ground, &amp;c. Anſ.</hi> In the originall it is not ſo, but by way of interrogation, as the moſt famous Interpreters <hi>Tremellius</hi> and <hi>Iunius</hi> do tranſlate it. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t vivit Iehova, an cadere debet ullus è capillis capitis ejus? as the LORD liveth ſhould there fall any haire of his head to the ground?</hi> The people adjure <hi>Saul,</hi> and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale his Conſcience <hi>before the living God</hi> (ſay theſe lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Interpreters) <hi>ut poſthabitâ juramenti ratione, juris habeat rationem:</hi> as if they had ſaid, is it reaſon that he ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the leaſt hurt from the people, who following the Lord hath wrought ſo great Salvation to the people? Then they defended <hi>Ionathan</hi> not by armes, but by ſound reaſon; which kind of defence is moſt willingly granted by his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty to all that now cry for armes.</p>
               <p>Your next teſtimony is no more worth. The people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were put to no ſmall ſtrait, when there was no Smith in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> but were forced to go down to the <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtines,</hi> to ſharpen their <hi>ſhares,</hi> their <hi>axes,</hi> and <hi>mattocks.</hi> This is alſo your caſe, you muſt here go to the enemies, and from the Papiſts borrow weapons to defend your cauſe, in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of <hi>Vzziah</hi> and <hi>Athaliah:</hi> Wherby they maintain the <hi>Supremacy of Pope</hi> over <hi>Kings,</hi> and you now uſe them to maintain the <hi>Power of the people</hi> over <hi>Kings.</hi> But let us conſider them. The firſt is of <hi>Vzziah</hi> the King, who contrary to Gods Commandement, went into the Temple
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:19621:25"/>of the Lord <hi>to burn incenſe upon the Altar.</hi> And <hi>Azariah</hi> the Prieſt went in <hi>after him, and withſtood him, &amp;c. Anſw.</hi> 1. By this example, you muſt either maintaine, that the <hi>Subjects</hi> are above the <hi>Prinee,</hi> giving them the Popes uſurped authority; or if not, you muſt help to anſwer this your ſelves, &amp; ſo looſe the knot which your ſelves have knit. The Papiſts ſay,<note place="margin">2 Chron. 26.</note> 
                  <hi>That the High-Preiſt thruſt the King out of the Temple, when he uſurped the Prieſts office,</hi> ergo, <hi>the Pope is above Kings;</hi> the reaſon of the inference is, becauſe no <hi>Inferiour</hi> hath power to lay hands on a <hi>Superiour,</hi> and by <hi>coactive power.</hi> to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell them to doe their duty, or repell them. Now you ſay the ſame, <hi>The High-Prieſt thruſt the King out of the Temple, therefore it's lawfull for the people to reſiſt Kings.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bellar. de Pont. Rom. lib. <hi>15.</hi> cap. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note> What rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon can you give of this inference, except you acknowledge the <hi>peoples ſuperiority</hi> above the <hi>Prince;</hi> and certainely, in your comparing the <hi>King</hi> and his <hi>Subjects,</hi> you ſeem to hold it ſo. 2. The Prieſt thruſt out the King <hi>not by</hi> taking <hi>armes,</hi> but with <hi>rebuke</hi> and <hi>admonition,</hi> as the Text is cleare, <hi>It per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth not to thee <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zziah to burne incenſe,</hi> and bad him de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part out of the <hi>Sanctuary.</hi> This became the Prieſt to doe. But what did the King? He was <hi>indignabundus,</hi> he was wroth, diſdained their rebuke, and took the Cenſer in his hand to burn incenſe. What followed upon this? The Prieſts admonitions being contemned, then the Lord tooke order with him, to whom it onely belonged. <hi>While the King was wroth with the Prieſt</hi> (ſayes the Text) <hi>the leproſy roſe up in his forehead, before the Prieſts:</hi> then no man needed to bid him depart, for the Text ſayes, <hi>He himſelfe haſted to goe out, becauſe the Lord had ſmitten him.</hi> It was not then <hi>violence</hi> from the prieſts, but the <hi>puniſhment</hi> from God, that thruſt him out. But you will ſay, the Text ſayes alſo, that the Prieſt <hi>thruſt him out,</hi> ſo it doth, but it was by <hi>admonition</hi> and <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke;</hi> for the Text ſayes, <hi>The Prieſts looked on him, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold he was leprous, and they thruſt him out from thence, yea, he himſelfe haſted to goe out</hi> He knew not that he was ſo, till the prieſts ſeeing it, told him, and without-doubt, rebuked <hi>him ſharply;</hi> telling him of the judgement of God upon him.
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:19621:26"/>Thus doth <hi>Ioſephus</hi> teſtifie. <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>de Antiquit. Iud, cap.</hi> 11. Whom <hi>Cajetan</hi> followeth. <hi>Viſâ leprâ, ſacerdotes regem ad fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinè egred endum monent.</hi> The leproſie being ſeen, the Prieſts admoniſh him to make haſte to go out. So doth <hi>Chryſoſtam,</hi> and giveth the reaſon of it, ſaying; <hi>The office of a Prieſt is only to reprove, and freely to admoniſh, not to move armes, nor to uſe bucklers, nor to ſhake a launce, neither to bend a bow, and ſhoot forth darts.</hi> All then that can be drawne from this example is, 1. That when Kings break the Commandements of God by any ſcandalous fact, it's the Preachers duty to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke him. 2. That when Princes will not regard the admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitions of Gods Servants, they muſt be left to God, who ſometimes will viſibly puniſh them. I retort then your Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, <hi>Azariah</hi> did not by armes defend Gods <hi>right,</hi> as you call it, <hi>ergò,</hi> you ought not to take up armes, though you had an <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zziah</hi> to deale with.</p>
               <p>Your next example is of <hi>Iehojada, who commanded</hi> Athaliah <hi>to be ſlaine.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 King. 11.</note> The very bare reading of the Hiſtory anſwers you ſufficiently. <hi>Athaliah</hi> was an <hi>uſurper</hi> of the Crowne, which by right belonged to <hi>Ioaſh,</hi> which was hid ſix yeeres from her cruelty. After <hi>Iehojada</hi> the High-Prieſt, <hi>Ioaſh's</hi> Uncle and Tutor with the <hi>Captaines</hi> and <hi>Hundreds,</hi> with the <hi>Levites</hi> and chiefe <hi>Fathers</hi> of Iſrael, had brought forth <hi>Ioaſh,</hi> and put on him the Crowne, and declared him King; then by authority of <hi>Ioaſh</hi> the King thus ſeated in his throne, <hi>Iehojada</hi> cauſed ſlay that bloudy uſurper of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome <hi>Athaliah.</hi> So this was done by the authority of the King. Now nothing can be gathered from this, but if any Subjects for certaine yeeres have taken upon them Royall authority, if the <hi>righteous King</hi> doe recover his own autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, he may command the <hi>uſurpers</hi> to be ſlaine. This point ſhall not be denied you.</p>
               <p>Your laſt example from Scripture is alſo againſt you, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the men of <hi>Keilah.</hi> If you wil without prejudice judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly conſider the place, you ſhall ſee that if you will prove the <hi>lawfulneſſe</hi> of your <hi>defence,</hi> it muſt be from <hi>Davids flying</hi> from <hi>Saul.</hi> I have often ſeene both in the <hi>Fathers,</hi> and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:19621:26"/>
                  <hi>Writers, Davids</hi> example produced for to ſhew the <hi>unlawfulneſſe</hi> of <hi>reſiſting</hi> Princes, but never till now, for the <hi>lawfulneſſe</hi> of reſiſtance. Conſider firſt then in generall, that as <hi>Saul</hi> was ever <hi>invading David,</hi> ſo he was ever <hi>flying</hi> from him. 2. That where <hi>David</hi> did hide himſelfe, he found oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times treacherous men to diſcover him, promiſing to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver him unto <hi>Saul.</hi> So the <hi>Ziphits</hi> ran to <hi>Saul,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Doeth not David hide himſelfe with us in ſtrong holds in the wood, in the hill of Hachilah? Now therefore, come downe, and our part ſhall bee to deliver him into the Kings hand.</hi> And thus being oft betrayed, he was forced to forſake the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome altogether, to goe to the King of <hi>Gath.</hi> Now for the men of <hi>Keilah,</hi> they were much obliged to <hi>David</hi> for deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering them from the <hi>Philiſtims;</hi> and therefore, the place being indebted to him, and alſo farre from <hi>Saul,</hi> he deſired to remaine there ſo long as he might, as having no certaine dwelling place elſe-where. <hi>Saul</hi> hearing that he was there, ſaid, <hi>God hath delivered him into mine hand: for hee is ſhut in by entring into a towne that hath gates and barres.</hi> By all ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance, it was ſome of <hi>Keilah</hi> that brought <hi>Saul</hi> this newes, ſhewing him what advantage, he now might have of <hi>David,</hi> being in ſuch a cloſe towne. As for <hi>David,</hi> being wiſe as the Angel of God, when he heard of his diſcoverie to <hi>Saul,</hi> he foreſaw that if the men of <hi>Keilah</hi> would bee un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfull, they might keepe him within the towne to the King, and not ſuffer him to flie away. Therefore he enquires of God, firſt, if <hi>Saul would come there to ſeeke him,</hi> for hee had no purpoſe to goe from <hi>Keilah,</hi> if <hi>Saul</hi> were not to come; for, poore man, he had no place to goe to. Secondly, hearing that <hi>Saul</hi> would not faile to come downe, hee began to ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect the men of <hi>Keilah</hi> of deceit, that they would ſhut the gates, and keep him in, till the King ſhould take him, having ſuch advantage of the gates and barres, that hee could not flie, as his uſuall cuſtome was. Therefore hee demands of God the ſecond time, <hi>Will the men of Keilah deliver me,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Sam. 23, 12.</note> 
                  <hi>and my men into the hand of Saul?</hi> that which is here tranſlated <hi>(deliver,)</hi> in the originall is, <hi>ſhut up. Will the men of Keilah
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:19621:27"/>ſhut mee up?</hi> as is alſo exponed in the Margent of the Bible in that place. So the meaning is not as you moſt ſeditouſly expound it, <hi>Will the men of Keilah not defend mee,</hi> but deliver me to <hi>Saul,</hi> who am reſolved to keepe this walled Citie againſt him? But this is the meaning, <hi>Will the men of Keilab not let mee goe away, but ſhut me up, cloſe the gates, that I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not eſeape by flying?</hi> This lets us ſee, that <hi>David</hi> had a pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to flie from <hi>Saul,</hi> which makes him ſo carefull to try, whether the men of <hi>Keilah</hi> would hinder him by ſhutting their gates, that finding them deceitfull, he mightflee in time. And therefore it's without warrant, you ſay, that <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> with his ſix hundred men purpoſed to defend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in the citie agaiſt the King. If hee had purpoſed to keepe the towne, he would have beene well pleaſed, how cloſe ſoever the gates had been ſhut: and would rather have enquired, Lord, will the men of <hi>Keilah</hi> open the gates, and let in the King, then will they ſhut the gates upon me?</p>
               <p n="2">2 Though your expoſition were true, that <hi>David</hi> purpoſed to keepe the towne againſt the King, the queſtion yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth, Whether he ought to have done ſo, or not? <hi>a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cto, ad jus non valet conſequentia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3 It proveth not your concluſion. <hi>David</hi> was but one man, who tooke an army of ſix hundred men, to defend him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe againſt the King, as you dreame. Therefore, when the King perſecuteth a private man, he may gather an army and reſiſt the King: which I hope you will not, at leaſt, cannot ſuſtaine: and yet you muſt ſuſtaine this, or elſe paſſe from your Argument.</p>
               <p>Finally, if any of you were in the caſe that <hi>David</hi> was in, to be the <hi>Anointed of God,</hi> and appointed by God to <hi>ſucceed Saul,</hi> it feares mee you would take more upon you then <hi>David</hi> did, for ye have done more already: and ſome of you are not aſhamed to call the Nobility, <hi>Ephori,</hi> and that they put on the <hi>Crowne</hi> with the King in his Coronation, turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all to a finiſtrous and ſeditious ſenſe.</p>
               <p>As for your examples from reformed Churches, ſince we live not by <hi>Examples,</hi> but by <hi>Lawes,</hi> I will not ſtand upon
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:19621:27"/>them as not knowing the Lawes and Government of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Kingdomes. If they have Lawes for their reſiſtance, you produce theſe examples moſt impertinently. 2. From facts to prove the Lawfulneſſe of reſiſting is ridiculous. 3. None of theſe by <hi>reſiſting,</hi> gained ſo much as by <hi>ſuffering;</hi> as experience too late doth ſhew.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Covenanter.</head>
               <p>From Teſtimonies not onely of Popiſh Writers,<note place="margin">8. Argument.</note> but of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines of the reformed Churches, even ſuch as will bee ſtrong pleaders for Monarchie: Neither is <hi>Calvin</hi> againſt us, but for us; From the teſtimonies of moſt judicious Lawyers and learned men, who have written <hi>contra-Monarchomachos.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Anticovenanter.</head>
               <p>I grant Ieſuites (yet not all) are for your tenet, for herein you agree, contrary to the Doctrine of al ſound Divines, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient and moderne. You name not any Proteſtant Divine, but <hi>Calvin,</hi> who is flat againſt you; for this purpoſe, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre you to learne it out of the <hi>Duplie</hi> of the moſt learned Doctors of <hi>Aberdeen.</hi> You nominate no judicious Lawyers. I know your Advocate Maſter <hi>Iohnſtone</hi> is for you, but the queſtion is too <hi>Deepe</hi> for his <hi>ſhallow</hi> brain.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Covenanter.</head>
               <p>From the mutuall contract betweene the King and the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, as may be ſeene in the Acts of Parliament,<note place="margin">9. Argument.</note> and Order of Coronation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Anticovenanter.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. To this, I give a <hi>Reall</hi> and <hi>Royall</hi> anſwer from the moſt gratious and moſt learned King <hi>Iames</hi> of Bleſſed me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, in his Booke intituled, <hi>Ius Liber a Monarchiae,</hi> pa. 193.
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:19621:28"/>
                  <hi>Nego ego tempore Coronationis inter regem &amp; ſubditos pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum ini<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i, &amp;c.</hi> I deny ſayes he, that in the time of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronation, there is any ſuch covenant betweene the King and his Subjects. But this is manifeſt, that at that time, or at the beginning of his raigne, <hi>ſponte ſuá,</hi> of his owne accord, the King promiſeth to diſcharge honeſtly and faithfully that charge, which God hath committed and entruſted him with. 2 Though it were granted that there were ſuch a mutuall contract, yet his Majeſty demonſtrates moſt clearely, that it cannot helpe this cauſe. If the King, ſayes hee, ſhall not keepe his part of the Covenant, who ſhall be judge between theſe parties? there is none who hath but attained to a ſmal taſte of the civill Law, who knoweth not, that the contract cannot be eſteemed violated by the one partie: nor the other abſolved of his part of the contract, before that it be made manifeſt by the cognition and Tryall of the ordinarie judge, which of the parties hath departed from the Contract. For this is the caution of every <hi>civill</hi> and <hi>municipiall</hi> Law; other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe what could hinder but that every man, in his <hi>owne cauſe</hi> may be both <hi>Judge</hi> and <hi>partie,</hi> then the which, there can bee nothing thought more abſurd. Now in that contract be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the King and his Subjects, without all controuerſie onely God is <hi>Iudge,</hi> to whom alone the King is bound to give acount of his adminiſtration; becauſe in that oath at the Kings inauguration, both the judgement and vengeance of his perfidious dealing is given onely to God. Therefore ſince God alone is the judge between the parties, and ſince the try all and vengeance onely doth belong to him, it muſt neceſſarily follow, that God muſt firſt pronouce the ſentence againſt the King, before the people can be thought free of their part of the Covenant, of <hi>obedience</hi> and <hi>ſubjection.</hi> And ſo there is no man ſo blind, but he may ſee how unjuſtly you make your ſelfe <hi>judge</hi> in your <hi>owne cauſe,</hi> and uſurpe the <hi>place</hi> of God. 3. From this your mutuall contract, you muſt ſhew that his Majeſty, not only obligeth himſelfe to performe his Kingly office, but alſo giveth power to the people (when they judge that he failes in his part) to reſiſt him by force of
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:19621:28"/>armes: or elſe, you are idle to alleadge ſuch contract. And if you will produce this. I have no more to ſay, but that the King hath denuded himſelfe of <hi>Royall authority,</hi> and devol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved it into the peoples hands, he onely in name, and the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in effect, being King and ſupreme judge in their owne cauſe: and ſo the King muſt ſtand, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t magna nominis um<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bra.</hi> But you would doe well, to produce ſuch a contract out of the <hi>Vtopia</hi> of your owne braine.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Covenanter.</head>
               <p>From Acts of Parliament ratifying the three Eſtates Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,<note place="margin">10. Argument</note> and from our owne eccleſiaſticall and civill Hiſtorie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Anticovenanter.</head>
               <p n="1">1 There can be no Acts of Parliament, but thoſe the King ſets downe with advice of his Eſtates. 2 And can you ſhew any Act of Parliament for the lawfulnes of reſiſting Princes, or can you ſhew that there is any Act of Parliament, giving authority to the Eſtates, to reſiſt His Majeſty to execute Iuſtice? 4 Doe you attribute any authoritie to theſe, which ye cal the three Eſtates, without the King? You muſt know, that the King is the onely <hi>Law-giver,</hi> the Parliament is but his <hi>extraordinarie Councell,</hi> and the Eſtates thereof are his <hi>extraordinarie Counſellours,</hi> by whoſe advice hee enacts Lawes. Conſider alſo, there was no Law in the Kingdome of <hi>Scotland</hi> before the Kings of it; for, before <hi>Ferguſius</hi> his dayes, we were but like <hi>Saluſticus Aborigenes. Genus homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num agreſte, liberum at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſolutum, ſine legibus, ſine imperio.</hi> But when the firſt King did conquer this Land, he and his Succeſſours gave Lawes, divided the whole Land which was their owne; and diſtinguiſhed the orders of men, and did eſtabliſh a politicall government. This is clear by our Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicles, and <hi>Ex archivis regijs, in quibus antiquum &amp; pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maevum jus aſſervatur, ſatis conſtat,</hi> Regem eſſe Dominum omnium bonorum directum, omnes ſubditos eſſe ejus vaſſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:19621:29"/>qui latifundia ſua, ipſi do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ino referant accepta, ſui nempé obſequij &amp; ſervitij praemia. 4 If you attribute ſuch incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patible power to theſe Eſtates, Why did not you by vertue thereof conclude this warre? You ought firſt to hold a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and then conclude warre. But pardon me, you have done ſo, Your <hi>three Tables is for</hi> Your <hi>three Eſtates,</hi> which hath ordained this warre. 5. Which are theſe <hi>three Eſtates</hi> now? <hi>Epiſcopacie</hi> is thruſt from you, and <hi>over-ruling El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> are in their place, who are buſie Biſhops in another mans Dioceſſe, and have been too buſie in my pariſh; And ſhall they ſupply their place in Parilament? As for your <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall and civill Hiſtorie,</hi> if that be <hi>Knox, &amp; Buchanans regni jus,</hi> expreſly condemned by Act of Parliament, you may be aſhamed to name them, and ought to have covered their nakedneſſe if you had reſpected them, You have publiſhed in print to the great diſgrace of <hi>Knooe,</hi> that he called knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling at the Communion, <hi>An Invention of the Divell,</hi> and will you here make him a <hi>Doctor of Treaſon?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Covenanter.</head>
               <p>From our Covenant lately ſworne and ſubſcribed,<note place="margin">1. Argument.</note> binding us to defend the Kings Majeſties perſon, in defence of the true Religion, and to defend the true Religion againſt all perſons whatſoever.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Anticovenanter</head>
               <p>This is indeed <hi>Ilias malorum,</hi> your Covenant binds you to it, and to much more, even to whatſoever ſhall ſeem good to the moſt part of you by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon conſent, were it never ſo hai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous. <hi>For that clauſe of your Covenant, wherein you are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to whatſoever ſhall ſeeme meete by common conſent,</hi> is a great Ocean, a blanke, to be filled up with what you pleaſe, it ſeemeth good to you already for the keeping of the firſt Table, to break the ſecond, in working the works of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſſe. As to with-hold from Miniſters their Sti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend, as conducible for your ends, to threaten them with
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:19621:29"/>big words, to lay violent hands on them in the diſcharge of their calling in pulpit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> which I have ſuffered; and which is more, to contemne and diſobey <hi>Supreme, Authoritie;</hi> yea, to take up armes againſt it: and if you by common con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, ſhall thinke meete to remove that blocke of authoritie out of your way, you are obliged to it by your Covenant: for certainely, this is very conducible to your ends. For if your <hi>Calder wood</hi> be true, Kings are enemies to Religion, in his <hi>Altare Damaſcenum,</hi> he affirmeth, that <hi>Natura inſitum eſt omnibus regibus odium in Chriſtum.</hi> And ſo King <hi>James</hi> of Bleſſed memorie is called by him <hi>Infeſtiſſimus eccleſiae hoſtis,</hi> And your Maſter-man <hi>Cartwright</hi> layeth down a ground for this overthrow of Kings, (as you may reade <hi>in the ſpeech de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered at the Viſitation of Downe and Conuer,</hi> by the right reverend and moſt learned Biſhop of <hi>Down:</hi>) for he hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that the <hi>Common-wealth</hi> is in the Church, and not the Church in the <hi>Common-wealth:</hi> and therefore, as a wiſeman will not frame his houſe to his hangings, but his hangings to his houſe; ſo the Church is not to bee fitted to the <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> but the <hi>Common-wealth</hi> to the Church. This gear goeth right, for then, as there is a <hi>paritie</hi> in the Church (for ſo you will have it) there muſt be alſo a <hi>parity</hi> in the <hi>State,</hi> and ſo, let <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Biſhops</hi> goe together. Thus King <hi>Iames</hi> knew full well the myſterie of your Religion, whilſt he made theſe convertible. no <hi>King,</hi> no <hi>Biſhop,</hi> no <hi>Biſhop,</hi> no <hi>King.</hi> And in your third argument, you tell <hi>that the people makes the Magiſtrate, and you may be without him,</hi> and by all appearance, <hi>you have</hi> (that I may uſe your owne words) <hi>rid your ſelves of him too, as an author and executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oner of your woes;</hi> and have ſet up a new ſort of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of 26. Governours, yearly changeable, for managing the affaires of the Kingdome: conſiſting of <hi>Nobles, Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons and Burgeſſes,</hi> which government will trouble all our Politicians to give it a name, for it's neither a <hi>Monarchie,</hi> nor <hi>Ariſtocracie,</hi> not <hi>Democracie,</hi> nor <hi>Oligarchie, &amp;c.</hi> And you will offend, if we call it, <hi>Anarchie. When there was no King in Iſrael, every man did what ſeemed good in his fight.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:19621:30"/>
               <head>Covenanter.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>It's objected; that although upon the former reaſons it cannot be denyed, but it muſt be lawfull for ſubjects to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend themſelves by armes, againſt the unjuſt invaſion or op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of the Magiſtrate; yet the matters preſently debated betwixt the King and his people, are neither fundamentall in Religion, nor of that importance, that wee ſhould enter into a bloudie warre, which bringeth with it ſo many cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine evils, and whereof the event is uncertain.</hi> Wee anſwer <hi>1.</hi> No matter of Religion hath ſo great weight in the mindes of worldly men, that they will hazard their worldly Eſtates for any thing of that kind. <hi>Gallio</hi> careth for none of theſe things. <hi>Feſtus</hi> ſayes, that the Iewes had certaine queſtions againſt <hi>Paul</hi> of their owne ſuperſtition, and of one <hi>Ieſus</hi> which was dead, whom <hi>Paul</hi> affirmeth to be alive; if we receive him; the Romanes will come and deſtroy our place, and our Citie, hath been a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing Maxime in policy. <hi>2</hi> The greateſt queſtions of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion carrie ſometimes a ſmall ſhew, witneſſe the words <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Electinomen,</hi> and <hi>Electi participium,</hi> which are ſmall in appearance, but great in ſubſtance. <hi>3</hi> There is a great miſtaking about fundamentall points of Religion, for if we call that fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, the knowledge whereof is neceſſarie for ſalvation, a point may be fundamentall and neceſſarie to be knowne at one time, or in one Kirk, which at another time, or in another Kirk, is not thus neceſſarie: for although the foundation it ſelfe bee neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie for the edification of everie ſoule, yet of things fundamentall, and neceſsary to ſalvation, wee muſt judge according to the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent degrees, and, meaſure of Revelation. There is alſo a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaking about the ſmalleſt matters of Religion, for obſtinacie in reſiſting the light, and following darkeneſſe rather than the knowne light in the ſmalleſt matters, brings certaine condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Jt was audaciouſly enacted by the Councell of <hi>Conſtance. Non obſtante Chriſti inſtitutione.</hi> The Kirk of Scotland, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving from the certaine knowledge of the Vnlawfulneſſe of Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcopall
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:19621:30"/>government (were it of never ſo little moment) abju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red it, diverſe times, and ſpued it out, we muſt not returne to our vomit. <hi>4.</hi> Though the queſtion were about the name of the Biſhop to be retained in our Church, as the crafty without any warrant give it out; yet were it moſt impertinent: for the queſtion muſt be taken either of the naked name, which no man is ſo ſilly to imagine, ſince we acknowledge it to be common to all the Miniſters of the Goſpell: or the queſtion is about the place and office ſignified by the name, which is to be a Paſtor of Paſtors without a particular flocke, to have the authority of Ordination and juriſdiction, to be a Lord of Seſsion, Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Councell Conuention and Exchequer, which either the Biſhop muſt be, or elſe, as they ſay themſelves, they cannot ſerve the Kings turne. He is willingly blinded, who ſees not how materiall this is: for beſides the ſinne in the office it ſelfe, it bringeth with it the ruine of all religion, by denuding the citie of her Walls, and the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ineyard of her hedge. It is either igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance or deception to ſpeake of Caveats: for if the Office be of Divine inſtitution, Why ſhould it be limited more then another office, or further then the Word of God doth require? Jt ought to bee rejected as a preſumptuous uſurpation upon the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Chriſt, in appointing chiefe Office-bearers in his houſe without warrant from him, and an intollerable derogation to his full and perfect Wiſedome, as if hee had not accompliſhed his Houſe with Offices and Office-bearers, but left them to the determination of the Wiſdome of men, which not onely in the Myſterie of Godlineſſe, but in the matters of Eccleſiaſticall Government, is enmitie againſt the Wiſdome of God. We have already had experience of Caveats, and now to hazzard ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrack the ſecond time, by making ſuch Pyrats againe to bee Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots, were deſperate madneſſe. <hi>5.</hi> But the Proclamation tels us, there are other matters of difference then Epiſcopacie. And laſtly, the queſtion is now, whether wee ſhall have a free natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Kirk, or any other Religion hereafter, but ſuch as is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by armes, the onely mid and Argument now uſed for that which is intended? and whether we ſhall any longer enjoy our Civill Liberty? for if baſe ſlaves be advanced to Honour
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:19621:31"/>they will labour to pleaſe the corrupt humours of thoſe who ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance them; theſe creatures muſt ſerve their maker. Time was when the Pope was maſter, and then they ſerved him. This time paſt, they have beene agents for Poperie, and as they have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven lamentable experience, that they too well know the way to Rome; ſo may we looke no leſſe, then that being re-advanced they ſhall carrie both Prince and people home againe to their old maſter, except wee ſtand faſt by our Libertie, wee can looke for nothing but miſerable and perpetuall ſlavery.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Anticovenanter.</head>
               <p>Theſe Objections are forged in your own brain, that you may the more eaſily anſwer them. There is no matter now debated of ſmall importance: it's neither Epiſcopacy, nor the Service-Booke, but of the Monarchie, and Supreme Authoritie of his Maieſty; So that upon your part there is no ſhadow of reaſon to take vp armes, but to yeeld all due obedience as it becommeth; and ſo farre as it concerneth his Majeſty, there is a neceſſity of armes, for the recoverie of his authoritie: And hee is not onely worldly minded, but <hi>treaſonably</hi> minded to take up armes againſt Authoritie under colour of Religion, 2. You ſay, <hi>the greateſt matters of Religion carrie ſometimes a ſmall ſhew.</hi> What is this to the purpoſe? I know no great queſtion in Religion, but for the matter it ſelfe, it muſt carry ſtill a great ſhew, and no ſmall; you bring grammaticall and nominall ſimilitudes of words, but for <hi>reall differences,</hi> they are very great. So <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritas Regis,</hi> and <hi>authoritas gregis</hi> carry great ſimilitude in words, but the reall difference is as great as betweene <hi>Monarchie</hi> and <hi>Democracie.</hi> But you make all the queſtion to be concerning <hi>Epiſcopacie,</hi> certainely herein the queſtion is neither ſmall in <hi>ſhew</hi> nor <hi>ſubſtance:</hi> for the queſtion is, 1. <hi>Whether Epiſcopall Government</hi> be <hi>Antichriſtian,</hi> and your new <hi>Preſbyteriall government</hi> that which Chriſt hath or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained in his Church, 2. Whether wee within the Church of <hi>Scotland</hi> are bound now to beleeve under the paine of
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:19621:31"/>damnation, your tenet concerning the government of the Church: and you hold that it is a point neceſſary to Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, now in our Church after ſuch <hi>degrees of light</hi> and <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation,</hi> to beleeve your ſayings. 1. But that is a miſerable light of yours, that non can ſee but your ſelves, your light is like <hi>ignis fatuus,</hi> which (as the learned ſay) flyeth from thoſe that follow it, and followes thoſe that flie from it. When we came to your Commiſſioners at <hi>Glaſgow,</hi> Maſter <hi>Retherfort,</hi> and Maſter <hi>Cant</hi> to aske reſolution of our doubts, your light fled from us, your anſwer was, <hi>Yee muſt denie rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and learning, and helpe Chriſt a lift.</hi> But while you were in Pulpit, you made the people to beleeve that you could <hi>ſolve</hi> all doubts, as having commiſſion from Chriſt ſo to do, let your <hi>light</hi> ſhine that we may ſee. Are all other Churches yet fitting in darkneſſe, not knowing rightly what is the Church Government, and you only a ſhining <hi>Goſhen</hi> in the midſt of <hi>Egypt?</hi> 2 If the knowledge of the unlawfulneſſe of <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> and the lawfulneſſe of your <hi>Preſbyteriall Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment</hi> be a point now ſo neceſſary, what is the cauſe that God never revealed, how his Church ſhould be governed all the time by-paſt? for you muſt have this by a <hi>revelation;</hi> and yet it muſt not be <hi>a divine revelation,</hi> becauſe it's contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to Gods Word, <hi>The Prophet that hath a dreame,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ier. 23.28,</note> 
                  <hi>let him tell a dreame, and hee that hath my word, let him ſpeake my word faithfully.</hi> Hath not the Church of Chriſt, that hath this 15. or 16. hundred yeeres been governed by <hi>Dioceſian Biſhops,</hi> beenlawfully governed? I am ſure if God had ordained your Government, he would not ſuffer his Church from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning to this time to have been blindly led. But for this point I remit you to the learned Writers for <hi>Epiſcopacie.</hi> As for your malicious aſperſions upon that <hi>Apoſtolike Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> becauſe you ſpeak at randome without reaſon, I leave you in your choller, to cry out againſt them, as enemies to al Religion; Pirats, and miſguiding Pilots.</p>
               <p>And may it not content you what you have done? you have done worſe than the Pagan mariners did with <hi>Ionah,</hi> to caſt theſe your <hi>Pilots</hi> over board into the Sea, (and how ſhall
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:19621:32"/>you govern the Ship in this ſtorme!) you have done worſe than the Souldiers would have done with the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 27.42.</note> who would kill him; for you have had ſuch relation with Satan in this work, that you have given them as a ſacrifice to Satan, as Satan would have given all the Kingdomes of the world unto Chriſt:<note place="margin">Luke 16.28.</note> but if you have really delivered them unto him, and he hath received them, there is a deepe gulfe wherein they are, that you need not fear their return to your Ship:<note place="margin">Acts 27.31.</note> nevertheleſſe I ſay unto you with <hi>Paul, That except theſe abide in the ſhip, you cannot be ſaved.</hi> And you ſhould ſtudie to know, what that is, to deliver over to Satan, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.5.</p>
               <p>But you ſay, <hi>You have ſpued them out of the Church, and cannot receive them. Anſ.</hi> 1. The Sea hath not been calme, but a great ſtorme hath wrought that exceſſe of loathing in your ſtomack. 2. The Church ſpued out all <hi>Popiſh errours,</hi> and amongſt the reſt, the <hi>Popiſh Hierarchie,</hi> and all <hi>Popiſh Biſhops,</hi> that hung upon the <hi>Pope,</hi> their <hi>Head;</hi> but they did not condemne the <hi>lawfull and laudable calling of Epiſcopacy,</hi> which is more ancient than the <hi>Pope,</hi> as ancient as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles. 3. If the Church hath ſpued out this lawfull calling (as I hope you will not make it good) ſhe hath been in a great diſtemper, and you ſhould have covered that fault, as <hi>Sem</hi> and <hi>Japhet</hi> did their fathers nakedneſſe, rather than <hi>Cham</hi>-like, to declare the ſame unto the world; it's our Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh proverbe, They are ſcant of newes that tels, their Father was hanged.</p>
               <p>Further, you ſay, <hi>The queſtion is now whether we ſhall have a free nationall Kirk, &amp;c. Anſw.</hi> 1. Are you beginning now to ſtate the queſtion, when you have ended your diſpute? 2. With ſuch a queſtion, How long will you wrong his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, who is ſo farre from taking armes againſt the Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on we now have, to eſtabliſh any other, that he will ſtill de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend our true Religion?</p>
               <p>You ſpeake of <hi>baſe Slaves,</hi> and cannot ſuffer that his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty ſhould advance them. But you ſpeake too baſely, and whence are you with your Nobilitie, you maſter Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:19621:32"/>with a Pope in your heart? you deſpaire of your ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement with <hi>Aerius,</hi> and cannot endure others. Such as he who ſaid, <hi>Make me a Lord above my Lady,</hi> and offered to leade a blinde Biſhop, that after his death he might be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to his place. The heels once murmured, becauſe they had not the place of the head; The Aſſe would climbe upon a Velvet Cuſhion to fawne upon his maſter, like a Spaniel. I pray you, whoſoever you be, who envie the advancement of learned men, or any others, to conſider, that the Kings ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects are as Counters in the Kings hand, whereof he makes one a 100. another a 1000. a third 10000. according to his pleaſure. And muſt he be countable to your humor? Or muſt you be his directer? You ſay, you muſt <hi>ſtand faſt to your liberty</hi> to withſtand the re-advancement of Biſhops. Take <hi>Peters</hi> counſell, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe not your liberty for a cloake of maliciouſneſſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Pe. 2.16, 17.</note> 
                  <hi>but as the Servants of God. Honour all men. Love the brotherhood. Feare God. Honour the King.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You began your reaſons with <hi>abſurdity</hi> and <hi>unreaſonable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> and you conclude with theſe laſt words, <hi>That you can looke for nothing but for miſerable and perpetuall ſlavery.</hi> So they deſerve that hold ſuch abſurdities.</p>
               <q>Pondus adeſt verbis, &amp; vocem futa ſequentur.</q>
               <p>And you muſt periſh in the <hi>gaineſaying of</hi> Core,<note place="margin">Iude 11. Rom. 13.2.</note> 
                  <hi>and receive to your ſelves condemnation,</hi> except ye repent, which I pray God to grant you. And as heretofore, <hi>You have faſted for ſtrife and debate, and to ſmite with the fiſt of wickedneſſe:</hi> So now I exhort you in the name of God to faſt and pray, that God would lighten your eyes in this Controverſie, and turne your rebellion, into an humble ſubmiſſion to God and your King.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:19621:33"/>
            <head>To my Brethren of the Presbyterio of <hi>DVNBARTAN.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reverend Brethren,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have received your Summons, the Tenor where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is thus: I Iames Thome <hi>Officer in that part conſtitute, ſummon you</hi> M. Iohn Corbet, <hi>Miniſter of Bonyl, to compeer before the Preſbyterie of Dunbartan the</hi> 16, <hi>day of April inſtant, to heare and ſee your ſelfe further cenſured for your former abſence from the Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and further contumacie and contempt to the Presbyterie, and other points both of unſoundneſſe of opinions, and diſobedience to the ordinance of the generall aſſemblie, as is evident by your manifeſt adhering to, and avowing of your declinator of the ſame, in your laſt preſumptuous and ſedicious letter, ſent to the moderator and remanent Brethren of the ſaid Presbyterie, written and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed with your hand of the date the</hi> 1. <hi>of April, with cortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, if you continue in your contumacie, and compeer not, you ſhall be</hi> ſimpliciter <hi>depoſed, from the function of the Miniſterie, at a perſon altogether unworthy of the ſanit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I pray you Brethren, have me excuſed, that I cannot compeer, ſince I have received your ſummons out of due time, and there is no paſſage between <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> becauſe of the great ſtormes from your coaſts, which are ſo great,<note place="margin">Pſal. 55.6, 8.</note> that I wiſhed the <hi>wings of a dove to ſtie away, and be at reſt;</hi> and by Gods good helpe, <hi>I have haſtned my eſcape from the windie ſtorme and tempeſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 57.1.</note> and come to <hi>Ireland,</hi> where <hi>in the ſhadow of the Lords wings, I ſhall make my refuge, untill theſe calamittes be over-paſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſa. 33.17, 20.</note> 
               <hi>and may ſee the King in his beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and Ieruſalem a quiet habitation: For this is the day of the Lords vengeance,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay 34.8.</note> 
               <hi>and the yeare of recompences for the contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies of Zion.</hi> In the meane time, if this my Treatiſe can finde paſſage by any meanes, and come to your hands, it wil either juſtifie me, or augment my fault; the one, if you be not prejudicated; but the other, if you be yet in your paſſions My Epiſtle which I deſired you to put on record <hi>ad futuram rei memoriam,</hi> as being able to make good what I have ſayd, doth contain theſe opinions following, which you moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoundly
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:19621:33"/>call unſound, and my letter preſumtuous and ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious. My 1. unſound opinion is, that I cal taking up of arms againſt the <hi>Lords Anointed,</hi> a doctrin of unrighteouſneſs. My 2. unſound opinion is threefold, that J ſaid, I take God to witneſſe, that I cannot ſubſcribe your covenant, except I would 1. ſin againſt God, 2. contemne Authority, 3. and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jure my Chriſtian Liberty. For the 1. I cannot but ſin againſt God, if I keepe not the oath of God, and obey the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of my King,<note place="margin">Eccles. 8.1.</note> againſt whoſe Authoritie &amp; Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement this covenant is ſubſcribed. 2 There muſt bee <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of Authority</hi> (and this is too milde a word, let me call it by it's owne name, <hi>Rebellion</hi>) if I ſubſcribe your covenant, for theſe 5 Reaſons. 1 becauſe all covenants are expreſly diſcharged by Act of Parliament, without his Majeſties pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie conſent be obtained thereto. 2 becauſe this covenant is expreſly forbid by his Majeſties Proclamations. 3 becauſe this your covenant containeth many unlawfull things, amongſt which, is that unlawfull Band againſt the <hi>Lords Anoynted.</hi> 4 Though your covenant were good and lawfull, yet, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept you prove that it's abſolutly neceſſary to be ſubſcribed, how dare any ſubſcribe it, being forbidden by authoritie without high <hi>contempt?</hi> 5. Since I have ſubſcribed the Kings Covenant, I cannot ſubſcribe yours without perjurie, as is clear in this treatiſe. And ſince you hindered your flocks to ſubſcribe the Kings Covenant, ſaying, they would be perju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, if they did it; how can I ſubſcribe both without per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurie? The third point, That by ſubſcribing, I muſt ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jure my Chriſtian libertie, wherein I ſhall ſtand faſt. I pray you, ſince your covena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t doth abjure things indifferent (ſuch as the Articles of <hi>Perth</hi> are. &amp;c.) as heads of Poperie, Doe I not thus far abjure my Chriſtian liberty, if I ſubſcrib? My laſt unſound opinion is of your aſſemblie. I was content &amp; ſhall ſtill remain, to paſſe from my proteſtation againſt your aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblie, theſe 3 grounds being proved. 1. That by acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging the authority of it, I be not obliged to beleeve the lawfulnes of it's acts, for it cals evill, <hi>good;</hi> and good, <hi>evill.</hi> 2. That it be proved by the laws of the kingdom, that when
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:19621:34"/>the King diſchargeth the aſſembly to ſit, it ought to refuſe, and ſit ſtill. 3. That it be made good, that when controverſie is between the King and the aſſembly, the aſſembly muſt be judge. In my preſumptuous and ſeditious letter, I called theſe grounds abſurd, and altogether derogatory to <hi>Royall authority,</hi> renting the <hi>Kings ſupremacy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And I appeale the conſcience of every one of you, whether theſe my opinions be unſound, and I for them judged un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of the Miniſtry; which if you do, your <hi>presbytery</hi> is the <hi>ſeat of violence,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amos 6.3.</note> to the which I will not <hi>come neare,</hi> where when <hi>judgement</hi> ſhould <hi>run downe as water, and righteouſneſſe as a mighty ſtreame,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amos 5.24.</note> you <hi>turn judgement into gall, and the fruit of righteouſneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amos 6.12.</note> 
               <hi>into Hemlock.</hi> Howbeit all reformed Churches in Europe are condemning your courſe, yet you ſay you are <hi>wiſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 8.8.</note> 
               <hi>and the Law of God is with you;</hi> yet certainly, except ye amend and change your opinions and waies,<note place="margin">Ier. 7.28.</note> 
               <hi>truth is periſhed and cut off from</hi> your <hi>mouths.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 23.14, 5.</note> This is the cauſe, that from you the <hi>Prophets of Jeruſalem, wickedneſſe hath gone over all the land, and the hand of evill doers is ſtrengthened, that none doth returne from his wickedneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 33.15.</note> but goe on with a revolting and rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous heart: it is good to <hi>walke righteouſly, and ſpeake uprightly,</hi> which is a hard thing to doe with you, when men muſt be over-rul'd with ignorant lay-Biſhops, to whoſe humor all muſt preach, who remember not that, one day in <hi>proper per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> we muſt give account to God, how we have taught our people to ſerve God and the King; againſt whom too many of you inceſſantly ſtir up the people, as againſt a <hi>Nero.</hi> I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort you my brethren, that when you are Evening and Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in private with God in your prayers, to remember and conſider whether your courſe be good or evill, which you continue in; and if your conſcience accuſe you, I pray God ye may be as earneſt to ungird that armour, as you have been in putting it on: And may ſhake off Puſill animity, having your <hi>faces ſtrong againſt their faces,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek, 3.9.</note> 
               <hi>who are</hi> ſeditious; <hi>and your foreheads ſtrong againſt their foreheads; not fearing them nor being diſmaid at their looks, though they be a rebellious houſe.</hi> Thus at laſt becomming <hi>valiant for the truth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 9.3.</note>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:19621:34"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
